<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The want of church-government no warrant for a totall omission of the Lords Supper. Or, A brief and scholastical debate of that question, which hath so wonderfully perplexed many, both ministers and people. Whether or no, the sacrament of the Lords Supper may (according to presbyterial principles) be lawfully administred in an un-presbyterated church, that is, a church destitute of ruling elders. Wherein the affirmative is confirmed by many arguments, and cleared from objections, especially such as are drawn from the unavoidablenesse of mixt communions without ecclesiastical discipline. / By Henry Jeanes, minister of Gods Word at Chedzoy in Sommerset-shire.</title>
            <author>Jeanes, Henry, 1611-1662.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1650</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 184 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 41 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A87512</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing J511</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E618_6</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R202652</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99862867</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99862867</idno>
            <idno type="VID">115045</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A87512)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 115045)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 95:E618[6])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The want of church-government no warrant for a totall omission of the Lords Supper. Or, A brief and scholastical debate of that question, which hath so wonderfully perplexed many, both ministers and people. Whether or no, the sacrament of the Lords Supper may (according to presbyterial principles) be lawfully administred in an un-presbyterated church, that is, a church destitute of ruling elders. Wherein the affirmative is confirmed by many arguments, and cleared from objections, especially such as are drawn from the unavoidablenesse of mixt communions without ecclesiastical discipline. / By Henry Jeanes, minister of Gods Word at Chedzoy in Sommerset-shire.</title>
                  <author>Jeanes, Henry, 1611-1662.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 72 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Samuel Gellibrand, at the Ball in Pauls Church-yard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1650.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Nouemb: 30".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Liturgy --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Presbyterianism --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Lord's Supper --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Church history --  17th century --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>Zev Berger</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>Zev Berger</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:115045:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>The want of CHURCH-GOVERNMENT No warrant for a totall omiſſion Of the <hi>LORDS S<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>PPER.</hi> OR, A brief and Scholaſtical debate of that <hi>Queſtion,</hi> which hath ſo wonderfully perplexed many, both Miniſters and people.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Whether or no, The Sacrament of the Lords Supper may (according to Presbyterial principles) be lawfully adminiſtred in an un-Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terated Church, that is, a Church deſtitute of Ruling Elders.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Wherein the Affirmative is confirmed by many Arguments, and cleared from Objections, eſpecially ſuch as are drawn from the unavoidableneſſe of mixt communions without Eccleſiaſtical Diſcipline.</p>
            <p>By HENRY JEANES, Miniſter of Gods Word at <hi>Chedzoy</hi> in <hi>Sommerſet</hi> ſhire.</p>
            <figure/>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for SAMUEL GELLIBRAND, at the Ball in <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard. 1650.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="approbation">
            <pb facs="tcp:115045:2"/>
            <head>An Approbation of the following Tractate, by that learned Divine M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. ROBERT CROSSE, late of <hi>Lincolne</hi> College in <hi>Oxford,</hi> unto whoſe cenſure it was ſubmitted.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Worthy friend,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> 
               <hi>Have ſomewhat heedfully peruſed your determination touching admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtring the Lords Supper in an <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>n-Presbyterated Church; It ſeems to me both judicious and accurate. I was of your judgment (as to the main) before. But am now much more enlarged and confirmed in it: If hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſober-minded men be not yet of the ſame mind with you, it is (poſſibly) becauſe they are unac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with your reaſons; You ſhall therefore to my apprehenſion, do both a grateful and ſeaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble work; To make that of publike uſe which may be, and I am confident will be of publike benefit.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Luckam,</hi> 
                  <date>
                     <hi>Novembr.</hi> 16. 1650.</date>
               </dateline>
Your friend and neighbour <signed>ROBERT CROSSE.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:115045:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:115045:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:115045:3"/>
            <head>To his honoured friend Col. John Pyne, A Member of the Parliament, and one of the Commiſſioners for the <hi>Militia,</hi> of the County of SOMMERSET.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg> Principall end of prefixing your name unto the follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing piece, is, to give a publike teſtimony of that deep obligation which lieth upon me, for thoſe fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours which you have vouchſafed un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to me; not in my ſelfe only, but in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers for my ſake. Theſe have beene ſo many and ſo great, as that they may
<pb facs="tcp:115045:4"/>make juſt challenge for you, unto any thing of my performance. But indeed this <hi>Treatiſe</hi> is yours by a ſtricter tye of juſtice, then that of gratitude; For it is principally by your care and aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, that it is brought unto the Preſs: and therfore to alienate it by any other inſcription, would be not only an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grateful, but an injurious part. I ſhall deteine you no longer from your more weighty affairs; But with my moſt hearty prayers commending you and yours to the great Preſerver of men, and beſeeching him to make you a wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy inſtrument of the peace and juſtice of this County; I ſhall reſt</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Yours in all humble obſervance, <hi>HENRY JEANES.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:115045:4"/>
            <head>To the Reverend our very much ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured Brother M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. HENRY JEANES, Preacher of the Word at <hi>Chedzoy,</hi> Theſe preſent.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Reverend Sir,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>E have met this day to debate whether there be any courſe warranted by the Word wherein Miniſters may proceed to the adminiſtration of the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, as our caſe now ſtands, and what that is? We earneſtly deſire that you would be pleaſed to take the Queſtion into your ſerious conſideration, and to give your thoughts on it, or rather the ſtate of it the fourth of</hi> July <hi>next enſuing, when we intend to meet again to conſult farther a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout that thing. And we are the rather inclined to deſire your particular reſolution therein; Becauſe we underſtand that you have adminiſtred that Sacrament, and therefore doubt not but you have ſome way ſatisfied your ſelf therein, which we earneſtly deſire that you would be pleaſed to impart unto</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your affectionate Brethren,
<list>
                     <item>Tho. Gatchel.</item>
                     <item>Rich. Newton.</item>
                     <item>Tho. Court.</item>
                     <item>Tho. Muſgrove.</item>
                     <item>Will. Mills</item>
                     <item>John Gardner.</item>
                     <item>George Newton.</item>
                     <item>Barthol Safford.</item>
                     <item>John Norman.</item>
                     <item>George Bindon.</item>
                  </list>
               </signed>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Taunton,</hi> 
                  <date>
                     <hi>June</hi> 13. 1649.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:115045:5"/>
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>PAge</hi> 2. <hi>line</hi> 21. <hi>for</hi> all <hi>read</hi> alſo for, <hi>p.</hi> 3 <hi>l.</hi> 5. <hi>for</hi> to <hi>r.</hi> ſo I. <hi>p.</hi> 5. <hi>l.</hi> 2. <hi>for</hi> by <hi>r.</hi> even by, <hi>p.</hi> 6 <hi>l.</hi> 35 <hi>for</hi> they <hi>r.</hi> they whom we oppoſe, <hi>p.</hi> 12 <hi>l.</hi> 14 <hi>for</hi> Are <hi>r.</hi> Is, <hi>p.</hi> 13 <hi>l.</hi> 6 <hi>for</hi> in-ductivum, <hi>r.</hi> inductivu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <hi>p.</hi> 15 <hi>l.</hi> 24 for <hi>nature,</hi> r. <hi>naturae, p.</hi> 17 <hi>l.</hi> 18 <hi>for</hi> is, <hi>r.</hi> in, <hi>idem, l.</hi> 32 <hi>for</hi> ſlock, <hi>r.</hi> flock. <hi>p.</hi> 18 <hi>l.</hi> 11 <hi>for</hi> preſuptuous, <hi>r.</hi> preſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptuous, <hi>p.</hi> 27 <hi>l.</hi> 78 <hi>for</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>r.</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>p.</hi> 32 <hi>l. laſt, for</hi> a duty <hi>r.</hi> be a duty, <hi>p.</hi> 38. <hi>for</hi> example <hi>r.</hi> example <hi>p.</hi> 41 <hi>l.</hi> 11. <hi>for</hi> codclude <hi>r.</hi> conclude, <hi>p.</hi> 43 <hi>l.</hi> 12 <hi>for</hi> ut <hi>r.</hi> ad, <hi>p.</hi> 45. <hi>l.</hi> 16. <hi>for</hi> more <hi>r.</hi> moſt, <hi>p.</hi> 50. <hi>l,</hi> 20 <hi>for</hi> proceeded <hi>r.</hi> preceded <hi>p.</hi> 52 <hi>marg. l.</hi> 21 for <hi>peccatur</hi> r. <hi>peccator, p.</hi> 54 <hi>l.</hi> 11. <hi>for</hi> poſſible <hi>r.</hi> poſſibly, <hi>p.</hi> 55 <hi>l.</hi> 18. for <hi>cocunque</hi> r. <hi>quocunque, p.</hi> 57 <hi>l.</hi> 1. <hi>for</hi> directions <hi>r.</hi> direction, <hi>p.</hi> 60. <hi>l.</hi> 5. blot out the ſecond, to, <hi>p.</hi> 61 <hi>l.</hi> 7 <hi>for</hi> ſin <hi>r.</hi> ſinners <hi>p.</hi> 63 marg. for <hi>te net-u</hi> r. <hi>te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>netur, p.</hi> 64 marg. l. ult. for <hi>hi</hi> r. <hi>hic, p</hi> 65. <hi>l.</hi> 6. <hi>for</hi> ſtances <hi>r.</hi> inſtances, <hi>p.</hi> 66 <hi>l.</hi> 20 <hi>for</hi> ſay <hi>r.</hi> ſee, <hi>p.</hi> 67 <hi>l.</hi> 14 <hi>for</hi> know <hi>r.</hi> knew, <hi>p.</hi> 69. <hi>l.</hi> 35 <hi>for</hi> re-eive rerecoive. <hi>p.</hi> 70 <hi>l.</hi> 29 blot out not, <hi>p.</hi> 72 <hi>l.</hi> 29 <hi>for</hi> committed <hi>r.</hi> committed by our ſelves.</p>
            <p>Theſe are the groſſeſt faults, others of an inferiour nature, being eaſily diſcernable by the Reader, are omitted.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:115045:5"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Whether or no the Sacrament of the Lords Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per may according to Presbyterial principles be lawfully adminiſtred in an un-Presbytera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Church, that is, a Church deſtitute of</hi> Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling Elders?</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>O go over the Topical places belonging to the Termes of the Queſtion, will afford the greateſt light: and upon a full and thorow ſurvey of them, I reſolve upon holding the Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion affirmatively.</p>
            <p>There be two Termes in the Queſtion conſiderable <hi>(viz.)</hi> Adminiſtration of the Lords Supper; and a Non-Presbytera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Church, or a Church deſtitute of ruling Elders: and I ſhall argue for the affirmative from both.</p>
            <p>Firſt then Arguments evidencing the Affirmative may be drawn from the Lords Supper, and the Adminiſtration there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of.</p>
            <p>From the Command of, and Examples for the admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration thereof.</p>
            <p>From the general Nature of the Lords Supper.</p>
            <p>From the Inſtrumental Cauſe, End, and Object of the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtration thereof.</p>
            <p>From a Compariſon of the Lords Supper with Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme.</p>
            <p>From the conſideration of the oppoſite of adminiſtration of the Lords Supper; the non-adminiſtration thereof.
<note place="margin">Primum â Praecepto.</note>
            </p>
            <p>The firſt Argument ſhall be taken from Chriſts Command, <hi>Luk.</hi> 22.19. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.24.25. <hi>This do in remembrance of me.</hi> All Chriſts Commands are to be obſerved, even in an un-Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterated
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:115045:6"/>Church, unleſſe there be ſome diſpenſation from Chriſt himſelfe to the contrary. The Charge that Chriſt gave to his Apoſtles at his aſcenſion, <hi>Mat.</hi> 28.19, 20. was to teach thoſe Nations they ſhould baptize, to obſerve all things what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever he had commanded them. Now to adminiſter the Lords Supper we have an expreſſe Commandement, and no diſpenſation that I know of, to lay it aſide in an un-Presbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated Church. <hi>Ergo,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>It is an old, and a good rule: <hi>Non diſtinguendum ubi lex non diſtinguit<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> We muſt not diſtinguiſh where the Law doth not diſtinguiſh. Limitations and reſtrictions of divine praecepts that have no foundation in Scripture are indeed ſaucy preſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, a taking upon us to tutour the Almighty.</p>
            <p>Unto this expreſſe Command for the adminiſtration of the Lords Supper the Scholemen adde a virtual and implicite pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept from the neceſſity,
<note place="margin">Suarez<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </note> or at leaſt profitableneſſe of it unto ſalvation. The people are bound to make uſe of all meanes that are in any degree neceſſary to ſalvation; and a Miniſter being to watch for the ſoules of his People, is to make what proviſion he can, not only of things ſimply and abſolutely neceſſary: but all things profitable &amp; convenient for ſalvation.</p>
            <p>Before I meddle with the Anſwer which may be to this Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument, I will give it a little more ſtrength. We have a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand not only for the celebration, but alſo for the frequent celebration of the Lords Supper. Mr <hi>Marſhal</hi> in his Sermon of the Baptizing of Infants argues for a repetition of the Lords Supper by way of Analogy and proportion from the Paſſeo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver. <hi>Pag.</hi> 35, 36.</p>
            <p>All Gods Commands and Inſtitutions (ſaith he) about the Sacraments of the Jews bind us as much as they did them in all things which belong to the ſubſtance of the Covenant, and were not accidental to them: The Jewiſh Paſſeover being to be yearly repeated binds us to have a repetition of the Sacrament of the Lords Supper, which came in roome of it: becauſe this belongs to the ſubſtance of the Covenant (both of them being Sacraments for ſpiritual nouriſhment, growth, and continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance in the Covenant.) But we have no need to ſtand upon a virtual or analogical command for the frequent uſe of this
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:115045:6"/>Sacrament, ſeeing we have an expreſſe command of it, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.24, 25, 26.
<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Addit decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rationem iſtius clauſulae hoc fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cite. Annunci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. Sic m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> quam Annun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciatis, quaſi di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cat annunciare debetis, nam exponit illa verba, Hoc fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cite ad meire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordationem. Quod ſi reddas Annunciatis: erit rationatio cujus vis nul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la apparet; Nempe vis Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinthii cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brantes Coenam Domini, Annun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciatis mortem Domini: ergo Chriſtus praece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pit ut hoc face<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retis. Quin &amp; determinatie illa temporis videtur impera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>em poſtulare, Annun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>iate do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nec venerit, id eſt, non ſolum vos ſed etiam vos ſecuturi credentes uſque ad finem mundi deb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nt in celebranda ſacra caena mortem Domini annunciare.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>This do in remembrance of me. This do as oft as ye drink it in remembrance of me: for as often as ye eate this bread and drink this cup, ſhew ye the Lords death untill he come.</hi> For to chooſe rather to read the words as they are in the Margent then as they are in the Tranſlation <hi>(ye do ſhew:)</hi> you may ſee in <hi>Piſcator</hi> two reaſons for thus rendring the words. The meaning of them in briefe is, Ye ought to ſhew, declare, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſent, and make known the death of the Lord by this ſacred Supper. This is a duty lying not only upon you, but upon all Beleevers following you unto the end of the world. The Lords Supper is then to be celebrated, even untill the coming of Chriſt to judgement; and therefore there ought to be no interruption of the celebration of it at fit and convenient ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, which is that which I meane by the frequent celebration thereof. That the frequent celebration of this Sacrament is a duty, is inferred from this Text by <hi>Tilemannus Heſhuſius, Fridericus Baldwinus, Peter Martyr, Calvin, Muſculus, Are<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius, Hiperius, Toſſanus, Pareus, Piſcator, Dickſon</hi> and our own <hi>Pemble.</hi> And for this their inference I find theſe follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing reaſons alledged: The firſt is preſſed by <hi>Pareus</hi> upon the words, <hi>Cur ſaepius faciendum, quia mors domini perpetuis lau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dibus celebranda,</hi> &amp;c. Chriſt death is ſo great, ſo important, ſo beneficial a mercy as that it cals for a frequent commemo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration. Now this Sacrament of the Lords Supper was ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed purpoſely to quicken our memory therein; <hi>Do this in remembrance of me;</hi> therefore ought frequently to be admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred.</p>
            <p>A ſecond reaſon is of Mr <hi>David Dickſon</hi> upon the place. Becauſe Chriſt ſhall not bodily be preſent in the Church be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the laſt judgment, he therefore commands that by this Sacrament the memory of the Redemption of the Church by his death ſhould ever and anon be repeated, and cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brated untill he come from the Heavens in the laſt day.</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:115045:7"/>
            <p>A third reaſon is alſo in <hi>Pareus</hi> upon the place: How long ought this Sacrament to be adminiſtred, untill the Lord come, till he come to judge the quick and the dead? For even as the Sacraments of the Old Teſtament continued untill the firſt coming of Chriſt in the fleſh; ſo ſhall the Sacraments of the New Teſtament continue till the ſecond coming of him in glory.</p>
            <p>From theſe Arguments thus premiſed we may infer in the words of the learned &amp; godly <hi>Pemble,</hi> that <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> here implyeth a <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>as often as ye do it,</hi> therefore do it often, not once in an age, as Baptiſme, never to be repeated; nor once a year and no more, as the Paſſeover; but many times in our Age, many times in a yeare, according as the Saints in the Primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Church underſtood the meaning of theſe words, and not as ſome in theſe times (when Sophiſtry hath wrangled out Divinity) would ſeeme to cavill that becauſe the words run, <hi>Do it as oft as you eate this bread and drink this cup,</hi> therefore it is at their diſcretion to do it as ſeldome as they pleaſe; who theſe Cavillers are that he ſpeaks of I know not: but <hi>Bellar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine</hi> hath ſome ſuch evaſion in his plea againſt the Cup in the Lords Supper; and <hi>Bullinger</hi> alſo upon the place hath ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing ſounding that way. By this word, <hi>As often,</hi> Chriſt (ſaith he) leaves a liberty unto the Churches when and how often they will celebrate the Lords Supper. For this he quotes a ſaying out of <hi>Auguſtine, Epiſt.</hi> 118. <hi>ad Ianuarium;</hi> In which after repetition of ſome variety, or difference in the Churches of God about the time of adminiſtring this Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, ſome adminiſtring it every day, and ſome only upon certaine ſet daies, he concludes that the beſt courſe for a pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent Chriſtian herein is to conforme himſelf unto the uſage of that Church unto which he ſhall come. Unto <hi>Bullinger</hi> I might joyne <hi>Hiperius,</hi> who quotes <hi>Epiphanius</hi> affirming as much. But I beleeve that the liberty left to the Church which <hi>Bullinger</hi> and <hi>Hiperius</hi> ſpeak of, is meant only concerning a prudent choice of fit and convenient ſeaſons for adminiſtration of the Lords Supper; alwaies provided that ſhe keep within the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude of frequency in the adminiſtration thereof. If ſo be by it they underſtand an abſolute unbounded liberty of admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtring
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:115045:7"/>it as ſeldome as ſhe pleaſe, the collection is ground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe and unreaſonable, and confuted by <hi>Volkellius</hi> a Socinian: and therefore an undervalluer of this Sacrament. We muſt mark, faith he, that the Apoſtle doth not at all ſay, that it is free for us to uſe, or not to uſe the Lords Supper; but he teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth us what we muſt do as often as according to the command of Chriſt we celebrate it (to wit, ſhew forth the death of the Lord) ſo that if the Apoſtle ſeem here to grant any liberty, it doth not ſtand in the uſage or neglect of this ſacred rite or ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remony; otherwiſe he ſhould be contrary to himſelf: For he ſaith that he received this Ordinance of the Lord, and that he delivered it unto the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> and in them unto all other ſucceeding Churches; that ſo it might be continued and uſed in the Aſſemblies of the faithfull, even untill the coming of Chriſt. I hope then you will give me leave to conclude, that howſoever <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> doth not abſolutely, and univerſally imply <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: yet it doth imply it in this place. If any deſire fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther proofes for the frequency of adminiſtring the Lords ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per; I ſhall deſire them to apply hereunto what I ſhall ſay touching the ends of the Lords ſupper. As alſo concerning the great need that Beleevers have thereof, even in an Un-Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terated Church. In the mean time I take it to be ſufficiently cleared, that we have here in the Apoſtle a peremptory com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand for the frequent celebration of the Lords Supper. And how we can obey this command, and yet omit the adminiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of it for 5,6,7. years together, nay perhaps for the whole ſpace of the remainder of our dayes, I am yet to learn. To ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe that we ſhall never live to ſee the Churches of God here in <hi>England</hi> ſetled in a Presbyterian way, is a ſuppoſition of that which is neither impoſſible, nor improbable. Now if the feares that many have concerning this particular ſhould prove true, What? ſhall the Lords Supper be for ever laid a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide? Would not this be a goodly interpretation of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, ſhew ye the Lords death till he come, that is, if you can get the Church to be Presbyterated, otherwiſe let there be a perpetuall amneſty as to the externall commemoration thereof? And yet this is the expoſition of the words which thoſe that diſſent from me in this Queſtion muſt hold, unleſſe
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:115045:8"/>they will retract their opinion, and confeſſe that the Lords Supper may bee adminiſtred in an Un-Presbyterated Church.</p>
            <p>I have bethought my ſelf what may be anſwered to this Argument <hi>a Praecepto,</hi> and theſe my thoughts I ſhall commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicate to you as plainly and briefly as I can. If any think that I propound the Anſwer feeble, I ſhall not be unwilling that they amend the propoſall, and adde what ſtrength they can thereunto. An anſwer may be grounded on what the School<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men ſay, <hi>in ſecunda ſecundae, Queſt.</hi> 43. <hi>Art.</hi> 7. Where <hi>Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas</hi> and all his Interpreters debate this <hi>Queſtion, An bona ſpiritualia ſint propter ſcandalum dimittenda?</hi> They reſolve that ſome things in themſelves, dutyes, and commanded by God to be done, yet are to be omitted at ſome times for the avoyding of ſcandal.</p>
            <p>Promulgation of a truth, and Chriſtian reproof are duties commanded by God; and yet are ſometimes to be abſtained from, for ſcandals taken, by not only the weak, but alſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litious. <hi>Reprove not a ſcorner, leaſt he hate thee, Prov.</hi> 9.8. <hi>ſpeak not in the ears of a fool; for he will deſpiſe the wiſdome of thy words, Prov.</hi> 23.9. <hi>Give not that which is holy unto dogges, neither eaſt ye your Pearles before ſwine, leaſt they trample them under their feet, and turne again and rent you,</hi> Math. 7.6. <hi>Pro vitando ſcandalo ceſſat rigor diſciplinae.</hi> To avoyd ſcandal the ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gor of diſciplineceaſeth<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> To explaine this; farther recourſe muſt be had unto that old and golden Rule, <hi>Affirmativa Praecepta ſemper obligant, non ad ſemper.</hi> Affirmative Precepts do alwayes bind, but not to alwayes; ſo that we are not bound to peforme alwayes what they enjoyne but only <hi>Loco &amp; tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pore debitis,</hi> when we have due time and place. Now as by the intercurrency of other circumſtances, ſo eſpecally by in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tercurrence of ſcandal, there may not be opportunity &amp; ſeaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nablenes of doing what we are urged unto by ſome Affirmative Precepts; ſo theſe Precepts may <hi>pro hic &amp; nunc,</hi> ceaſe to be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligatory. Now ſay they upon the adminiſtration of the Lords Supper in an Un-Presbyterated Church, ſcandall will enſew, a ſcandall tending to ſin in the unworthy receiver, who will be guilty of the body and bloud of the Lord; a ſcandall tending
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:115045:8"/>to ſorrow and vexation in the Well-affected, whoſe ſpirits will be ſadded at the communion of ſinners.</p>
            <p>For Reply. Firſt we muſt put a difference between a tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion of a Precept, and a temporary, partial, or occaſional forbearance of the matter commanded by a Precept. No Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept whatſoever is for the eſchewing the ſcandal of any to be truly broken or tranſgreſſed; and if a Precept be not tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſed, when what is enjoyned in it, is wholly and altogether omitted, I confeſſe I cannot divine when it can be tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed. <hi>Bonum per ſe</hi> (ſaith <hi>Suarez</hi>) <hi>praeferendum eſt ex genere ſuo bono per accidens.</hi> Now to adminiſter the Lords Supper is good <hi>per ſe &amp; ex genere ſuo,</hi> (I mean with a material obje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive or external goodneſſe:) to omit the adminiſtration thereof is only good <hi>per accidens</hi> in a caſe of ſcandal. And that which is only good by accident cannot always ſhut out that which is good <hi>per ſe.</hi> Suppoſe then that the adminiſtrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Lords Supper upon the emergency of ſcandal, may <hi>pro hic &amp; nunc,</hi> at ſome times and in ſome places be omitted, may for a while be forborn, untill we have uſed all means that lay in our power for the removing of the ſcandal, yet it wil not hereupon follow that after ſuch uſe of our utmoſt endeavours (and the ſcandal continue ſtill unremoved) the adminiſtrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Lords Supper is wholly and altogether to be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>born for five, ſix or ſeven years, or for the whole remaining ſpace of our lives. And it is only this latter that is broad e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to inferre, that the Lords Supper is not to be admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred at all in an un-Presbyterated Church. For a Church may be un-Presbyterated for ſo long a ſpace as we now ſpeak of, by means, Partly of the diviſions of the godly Party; Partly becauſe they may be oppreſſed by a predominant wicked Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty within, and perſecuted by adverſaries without: either of which (unleſſe timely prevented) is enough to retard the work of Reformation for more then the age of a man. That thoſe who talk only of a preſent ſuſpenſion of this Sacrament, do but ſhuffle and ſhift, would be eaſily apparent, if they would be pleaſed to ſpeak out, and tell us the latitude of this preſent ſuſpenſion, how long it ſhall laſt, when it ſhall end. I beleeve their opinion iffully diſcovered, will accord with
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:115045:9"/>thoſe of whom <hi>Muſculus</hi> ſpeaks, on 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. Now a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>days, ſaith he, thou ſhalt find very many, who in many years do not ſo much as once partake of this Sacrament; eſpecially the Swenckfeldians, who do ſo reject the Eccleſiaſtical Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion, of whatſoever Churches, that they themſelves had none at all. When at <hi>Auſpurge</hi> I asked a Ring-leader of this ſect, when he had partaken with the Church of Chriſt, of the Bread and Cup of the Lord; He expreſſy anſwered, he had then abſtained about twelve years from this Communion. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing demanded why he had done ſo, he replied, that he had not as yet found any Church, which was inwardly and out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly adorned with the gifts and vertues of the true ſpouſe of Chriſt; and that therefore he did put off and deferre his Communion, until he could find ſuch a Church rightly ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led or ordered.</p>
            <p>Here I ſhall once for all clearly prove, that a Miniſters uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal and total abſtinence from adminiſtration of the Lords Supper unto that flock or Church over which God hath made him an overſeer, is unlawful, though for the eſchewing of ſcandal. No ſinful omiſſion of that which is commanded by an affirmative Precept is lawful for the eſchewing of ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dal: But a Miniſters total and univerſal abſtinence from the adminiſtration of the Lords Supper, unto that flock over which God hath made him overſeer, is a ſinful omiſſion of that which is commanded by an affirmative Precept; therefore it is not lawful for the eſchewing of ſcandal. The major is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed from that of the Apoſtle, <hi>Rom<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> 3.8. Their damnation is juſt, that ſay, <hi>Let us do evill that good may come:</hi> as alſo that of <hi>Aquinas ſecunda ſecundae. Quaeſt.</hi> 43. <hi>Art.</hi> 7. <hi>Secun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum ordinem charitatis plus debet homo ſuam ſalutem ſpiritua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem diligere, quàm alterius.</hi> A well-ordered charity beginneth ever at home, making a man chiefly to deſire and endeavour the ſalvation of his own ſoul, and conſequently to be more ſoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citous how to avoid ſin in himſelf, then to prevent it in others; See <hi>Rutherford</hi> more largely touching ſcandal, <hi>pag.</hi> 84. The Minor is proved, becauſe it is neceſſary for my ſalvation to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey affirmative Precepts, though not in all differences of time. See <hi>Rutherford,</hi> pag. 13.14. <hi>Praecepta affirmativa obligant,</hi>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:115045:9"/>though not <hi>ad ſemper,</hi> yet <hi>ad aliquando.</hi> Affirmative Precepts tie us to do the things they require, though not at all times, yet at ſome time or other. And therefore univerſally and to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tally to abſtaine from what they command, is ſinfully to omit what is commanded by them. I cannot but here call to mind a Reply of the renowned <hi>Chamier</hi> to a ſhift of <hi>Cajetan,</hi> which he brings to elude our Arguments againſt their Communion under one kind, that are drawn from the command of the Cup. The Command, ſaith <hi>Cajetan,</hi> is but affirmative; and <hi>af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmativa Praecepta, utſi obligent ſemper, non tamen ad ſemper.</hi> Unto which <hi>Chamier</hi> replyeth very ſolidly and ſharply. <hi>Eſto</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>ſed quid tu appellas pro ſemper? nullumne apud te diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crimen eſt inter non ſemper? &amp; nunquam?</hi> The like Reply will ſerve unto thoſe who go about to evade the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of the Lords Supper, by telling us that it is an af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmative Command, and doth oblige <hi>ſemper,</hi> but not <hi>adſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per.</hi> It doth always bind, but not to always: for there is a wide difference between not always and never. Now the up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhot of theſe mens tenents, is, that if the Church be not Presbyterated, the Command of the Lords Supper doth ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver bind, during ſuch its condition. <hi>Suarez in Tertiam Part. Thom. Tom.</hi> 30. <hi>Diſput.</hi> 80. <hi>Sect.</hi> 1. as alſo <hi>Becanus</hi> in his <hi>Summae Theol. Scholaſtic. Part. tertiae Tract. ſecundo. cap.</hi> 25. <hi>Part. ſecundae. Quaeſt prima.</hi> alledge divers reaſons why all Prieſts whatſoever are bound to ſay Maſſe, if you pleaſe to make ſuch a change in them, as to put Miniſters for Prieſts, and the Lords Supper for Maſſe. you may make them Orthodox; and ſo they will ſerve our turn.</p>
            <p>Firſt, it ſeems to be a kind of ſpiritual Prodigality, very dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous to the ſoul, for a miniſter to deprive himſelf of the uſe of the power of order, and of the fruit of the Sacrament: Unto this we may adde out of <hi>Dunand,</hi> that it is a vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall contempt of the great benefit that is offered in the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, Seeing the power is for the Act, it is an inor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinate thing to receive the power of adminiſtring this Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and not to uſe this power, but to let it lye idle.</p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:115045:10"/>
            <p>Thirdly, It is againſt charity to deprive the Church of that great fruit and benefit which they might partake of by this Sacrament.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, Becauſe the Miniſter by vertue of his office, takes upon his ſhoulders the burden of praying for his people, of Preaching, and adminiſtring the Sacraments unto them; and therefore he ſins if he never or ſeldome diſchargeth theſe offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and duties of his calling. A calling and office is for the work<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Miniſtry and ſervice, proper thereunto; and therefore it is a great fault to neglect that work, ſervice or Miniſtry which is proper to a mans calling.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Not only a Miniſters totall and univerſall abſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nence from adminiſtration of the Lords Supper; but alſo ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domneſſe and unfrequency of adminiſtring it, is unlawfull. And the reaſon of this is, becauſe as I have proved and clea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red; There is a command for a frequent adminiſtration of the Lords Supper; And a command of frequency in diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation of an Ordinance is violated and tranſgreſſed, not only when the Ordinance is wholly and altogether omitted, but alſo when it is ſeldome or rarely diſpenſed, when it is omit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for the date of many years.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, This objection of ſcandall holds as well againſt ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtration of the Lords Supper in a Presbyterated, as in an Un-Presbyterated Church. For a Miniſter may ordinarily foreſee, that ſcandall will follow in a Presbyterated Church in caſe there be a Mal-adminiſtration of diſcipline, or elſe in caſe ſcandalous perſons known to be ſuch only unto the Miniſter himſelf, or elſe unto ſome one godly perſon, cannot be convi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, or proved to be ſuch, either by their own confeſſion, or elſe by the teſtimony of two or three witneſſes.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, It is a very unreaſonable poſition, that the admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtration of the Lords Supper ought to be ſuſpended, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred upon the likelyhood of the following of ſcandall; for then a Miniſter ſhall be almoſt perpetually uncertaine whether he may adminiſter the Lords Supper, or no; becauſe likely<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood of ſcandall to follow will occurre, if not alwayes; yet very often. When our Saviour tels us, <hi>Mat.</hi> 13.41. that in the conſummation, or end of the world, the Son of man ſhall
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:115045:10"/>ſend his Angels, and they ſhall gather out of his Kingdom all ſcandals, or all things that offend; he doth clearly imply that till then, there will be ſcandals even in his Kingdom, in his Church. And this holds not only of ſcandals in generall, but alſo of ſuch ſcandals as are likely to follow upon diſpenſation of Gods Ordinances unto the end of the world: Some will be ſcandalized at the Ordinances of God. The Word will be a ſavour of death unto death in them that periſh: Unworthy receivers will eat and drink their own judgment; will be guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the body and blood of Chriſt. Chriſt himſelf will be for a ſtone of ſtumbling, and rock of offence. You ſee then that to affirme, that the adminiſtration of the Lords Supper is to be deferred upon the likelyhood of enſewing of ſcandall, inferres this groſſe abſurdity, that the likelyhood of ſcandall extinguiſheth Chriſts gracious Charter of this Ordinance un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Church.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, If any one be not fully ſatisfied with that which I have ſaid, but ſhall demand farther in what difference of time the command to adminiſter the Lords Supper obligeth? Unto thoſe I anſwer briefly; that when a Miniſter hath uſed all ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liged means for prevention of ſcandall likely to follow upon his adminiſtration of the Lords Supper; that then he is bound frequently to adminiſter it unto the flock, or Church over which God hath placed him, eſpecially if they call and cry for it. In this caſe to delay it is a ſinfull omiſſion, and my rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon is; Becauſe unleſſe we pitch here, there can be no certain rule given, when a Miniſter is to adminiſter the Lords Supper. As for the aſſertion of thoſe who affirme that it is to be delay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in caſe of ſcandal conſequent, it is very unſound and irra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional; for if the lawfulneſſe or unlawfulneſſe of the admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration of the Lords Supper muſt be determined by the ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dal conſequent thereupon; the adminiſtration then of it hanges upon a very ſlippery and an uncertain ground.</p>
            <p>Sixthly, We muſt diſtinguiſh of ſcandals; they are either Active, or Paſſive, Given, or only Taken. The ſcandal fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing the adminiſtration of the Lords Supper in an Un-Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterated Church (eſpecially when a Miniſter hath uſed all obliged means for prevention of the ſcandal) is only Paſſive or
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:115045:11"/>Taken; not Active, or Given. And for this I dare appeale unto any definition of active ſcandal, or ſcandall given in any writer; either Popiſh, or Proteſtant.</p>
            <p>An Active ſcandal, or a ſcandal given, is, when one culpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly occaſioneth the fall of another into ſin: But a Miniſter in the adminiſtration of the Lords Supper in an Un-Presbytera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Church, (after that he hath uſed all obliged means for pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention of ſcandal thereby) doth not culpably occaſion the fal of another into ſin; for he diſpenſeth a neceſſary Ordinance of God; he performeth a commanded duty, which he cannot omit without ſin. Who ever, ſaith <hi>Rutherfurd,</hi> ſtumbles at the neceſſary Ordinances of God, they take a ſcandal which is not culpably given. Now how little reguard is to be had of paſſive ſcandals, ſcandals only taken are generally proved by Divines from the account which our Saviour made of the ſcandall of the Phariſees. <hi>Matth.</hi> 15.12, 14. <hi>Knowſt thou that the Phari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſees were offended after they heard this ſaying? But he anſwered let them alone:</hi> If any one deſire to know what the School<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men ſpeak of Active ſcandal, a ſcandal given: I ſhall briefly acquaint them what there is in <hi>Aquinas,</hi> who is one of the cheif of them; and make application of it to our matter in hand. <hi>In</hi> 2<hi>da.</hi> 2<hi>dae. Queſt</hi> 43. <hi>Art</hi> 1. We have this de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finition of Active ſcandal out of <hi>Hierome. Scandalum eſt vel dictum, vel factum, minus rectum, praebens alteri occaſionem ruinae.</hi> Two things I ſhall take notice of which he hath in the expli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of this definition.</p>
            <p>Firſt, <hi>Minus rectum non dicitur hoc quod ab aliquo alio ſupera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur in rectitudine: Sed quod habet aliquem rectitudinis defectum, vel quia eſt ſecundum ſe ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>um; ſicut peccatum, vel quia habet ſpeciem mali; ſicut cum aliquis recumbit in Idolo.</hi> From whence I thus argue, that wherein there is an Active ſcandal, a ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dal given, hath ſome morall irrectitude in it, is ſome way or other morally irregular; either becauſe it is evil in it ſelf, or becauſe it hath an appearance of evil: But the adminiſtration of the Lords Supper in an Un-Presbyterated Church, is neither evil in it ſelf, neither hath it a real appearance of evil, (for it is an Ordinance of God, a commanded duty.)</p>
            <p>Again, whereas it is objected that every word, or deed may
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:115045:11"/>occaſion the fall of another into ſin; <hi>Aquinas</hi> thus diſtinguiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth; <hi>Dictum vel factum alterius poteſt eſſe dupliciter altericau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſa peccandi, uno modo per ſe; alio modo per accidens; Per ſe quidem, quando aliquis ſuo malo verbo, vel facto intendit alium ad peccandum inducere; vel etiam ſi ipſe hoc non intendat, ipſum factum eſt tale, quod de ſui ratione habet; quod ſit in ductivum ad peccandum: Puta cum aliquis publice facit peccatum, vel quod habet ſimilitudinem peccati. Et tunc ille, qui hujuſmodi actum facit, proprie dat occaſionem ruinae: unde vocatur ſcanda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum activum. Per Accidens autem aliquod verbum vel factum unius eſt alteri cauſa peccandi, quando &amp; praeter intentionem ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantis, &amp; praeter conditionem operis, aliquis male diſpoſitus ex hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſmodi opere induci<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ur ad peccandum; puta cum aliquis invidet bonis. Et tunc ille qui facit hujuſmodi actum rectum, non dat occaſionem, quantum in ſe eſt: ſed alius ſumit occaſionem. Et ideo hoc eſt ſcandalum paſſivum ſine activo; quia ille qui recte agit, quantum eſt de ſe, non dat occaſionem ruine, quam alter patitur.</hi> Out of all this we may briefly obſerve thus much for our preſent purpoſe, that in an action there is then only an Active ſcandal, when either from the intent of the Agent, or elſe from the nature of the Action in it ſelf, it is inductive to ſin. Now to ſay that the adminiſtration of the Lords Supper in an Un-Presbyterated Church, is inductive to ſin, from the intent of the Agent, is uncharitable: To ſay that it is indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive to ſin from the nature of the Action in it ſelf, is a groſſe blaſphemy againſt an holy Ordinance of God.</p>
            <p>Seventhly, Whereas it is ſaid we may forbear the practice of things commanded by affirmative precepts, <hi>hic &amp; nunc,</hi> in ſome places, and at ſome times; it muſt alwayes be taken with this proviſo, that there be not incur'd a greater and more perilous ſcandal by forbearance, then would probably be oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſioned by practiſe of the thing commanded: which I beleeve is done in the forbearance of the adminiſtration of the Lords Supper, that is contended for.</p>
            <p>For firſt, if we ſpeak of the ſcandal tending unto ſorrow and vexation, more are ſcandalized at the forbearance, then in likelyhood would be at the practiſe.</p>
            <p>And ſecondly, if we ſpeak of the ſcandal tending unto ſin,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:115045:12"/>the ſcandal which the wicked take by the adminiſtration of of the Lords Supper is not to be compared with the ſcandals conſequent upon a total forbearance of the Lords Supper. (I mean in reference unto the Miniſter as chargeable upon him.) Here I ſhall firſt inſtance in the ſcandals tending unto ſin, occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioned by forbearance of the Lords Supper; and then compare them with thoſe which follow upon adminiſtration of the Lords Supper; and conſider of which the Miniſter is moſt guilty.</p>
            <p>Firſt, I ſhall inſtance in ſcandals tending unto ſin, occaſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by the forbearance of the Lords Supper.</p>
            <p>Firſt, There is the ſcandal of the godly, viz. their wants, and weakneſſe both of faith and grace, from want of an Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance appointed and ſanctified for the confirmation of faith, and increaſe of grace by the donour of all faith &amp; grace.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Seperatiſts are hereby encouraged in their ſepe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration from our Churches; becauſe we want a principal Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance of God, which alſo is laid aſide amongſt us upon a principle of their own, which was never granted them by the old Non-Conformiſts; to wit, that a worſhip is to be omitted for the ſin of the worſhippers, an Ordinance for the ſins of the partakers of the Ordinance.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, It ſtaggers many weak ones amongſt us, and if not timely prevented, will occaſion their totall defection and ſeperation from us. For though they approve not of their Tenents, yet this will much ſway with them; That amongſt them they may have an Ordinance, which amongſt us is with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>held from them, and of enjoying which, they have not any the leaſt hopes, as long as they ſtay with us.</p>
            <p>A fourth ſcandal is, in that others take occaſion by this forbearance of the Lords Supper, to contemne the Lords Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per it ſelf, as being by this carriage induced to beleeve, that Miniſters deſpiſe it, and do not ſo much for a while forbear, as utterly diſclaime the adminiſtration thereof.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Let us compare theſe ſcandals with the ſcandal which the wicked take by the adminiſtration of the Lords Supper, and conſider with which of them the Miniſter may moſt juſtly be charged. A Miniſter can never waſh his hands from theſe ſcandals which follow upon a totall forbearance of
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:115045:12"/>the Lords Supper; whereas having done his duty for preven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of that ſcandal, which the wicked take by adminiſtration of the Lords Supper, he ſtands free from the guilt thereof. My reaſon for this is, becauſe theſe ſcandals which follow upon a totall forbearance of the Lords Supper, are active as well as paſſive, given by the Miniſter, as well as taken be the People; whereas the ſcandal of the unworthy receiver conſequent to adminiſtration of the Lords Supper, is only Paſſive, not Active; taken by the unworthy receiver, not given by the Miniſter. The former ſcandals, thoſe which follow upon a totall for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bearance of the Lords Supper, flow <hi>per ſe</hi> naturally, and kindly from the Miniſters neglect or ſinful omiſſion of a neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary Ordinance of God.</p>
            <p>The latter ſcandal, the ſcandal of the wicked, their being guilty of the body and blood of the Lord, by occaſion hereor is only by accident, by reaſon, either of their ignorance, or ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full corruption, and evil diſpoſition. There is a young ſmatterer in both Divinity, and Philoſophy, who hath taken great exceptions againſt this paſſage; But he objected nothing worthy of the leaſt digreſſion: I ſhall therefore take no notice of what he ſayeth, but only clear, and explaine mine own meaning. When I ſay the ſcandals conſequent unto a totall forbearance of the Lords Supper, flow naturally there from: I mean <hi>congruenter nature;</hi> that is, ſutably and agreeably unto the nature of ſuch an omiſſion. The total omiſſion of the Lords Supper is of itſelf apt, and likely to occaſion theſe above mentioned ſcandals following thereupon.</p>
            <p>All ſinful words, deeds, and all ſinful omiſſions, (if diſcern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able by others) are in their own nature ſcandalous, they are of themſelves naturally apt to ſcandalize, to occaſion ſin in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers. Now I have proved that a total forbearance of the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtration of the Lords Supper is a ſinful omiſſion; and therefore, I think that it is no Paradox to affirme, that it natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally occaſioneth ſin in others.</p>
            <p>Again, whereas I ſaid, that the ſcandal of the wicked or unworthy receiver was only by accident: I meant <hi>in genere cauſae moralis.</hi> For <hi>in genere cauſae Phyſicae,</hi> the ſcandals con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequent unto a total forbearance of the Lords Supper, are by accident alſo.</p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:115045:13"/>
            <p>To manifeſt this, we muſt diſtinguiſh of a twofold cauſe of the ſcandal, or fall of another into ſin, Phyſical and moral; The Phyſical efficacious and neereſt cauſe, is only the ill-diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition and ſinful corruption of the Party ſcandalized; for all other mens words, actions, omiſſions are but occaſions, not cauſes of ſin <hi>in genere Phyſico,</hi> they work but objectively, and that is no Phyſical and real influence. And in this ſenſe I readily grant, that all paſſive ſcandals whatſoever, are accidental in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of the words, deeds, or omiſſions of others; the moſt enticing practices of others that are, even Satans temptations, have no real and Phyſical influence upon our ſins: but this acception of accidental, is utterly impertinent unto our pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent purpoſe. In a ſecond place then our ſinful words, actions, omiſſions, may be moral cauſes of other mens ſcandal, or fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling into ſin; they may ſcandalize (to uſe the words of <hi>Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therford</hi> morally) by contributing a moral influence culpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly to the ſcandalizing of others; to ſpeak plainly, all words, deeds, and omiſſions of either, that do ſinfully and culpably occaſion the ſcandal or fall of others into ſin, are moral cauſes of their ſcandal or fall into ſin. <hi>Moralis cauſa eſt, quae vere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quidem non efficit, ſed tamen talis eſt, ut ei imputetur effectus.</hi> But now if a word or action, do not ſinfully, culpably occaſion the ſcandal, the fall of another into ſin, but he only be ſcanda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lized thereby by his own default, that ſcandal is only termed then <hi>per accidens</hi> accidental, a paſſive ſcandal without an a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive, a ſcandal taken, not culpably given; ſuch was the ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dal in the Capernaites at Chriſts preaching, of eating his fleſh and drinking his blood<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <hi>John</hi> 6.60, 61. So alſo Chriſt crucified was to the Iews a ſtumbling block, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.23.</p>
            <p>In like manner the Phariſees were ſcandalized at Chriſts do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine concerning the cauſe of defilement, <hi>Matth.</hi> 15.12. All theſe ſcandals were only <hi>ex accidente,</hi> they were only acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dental ſcandals. Now to make application of all this to the matter in hand. The ſcandals in the godly conſequent, upon forbearance of the adminiſtration of the Lords Supper, how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever they come Phyſically from the ſinful corruption and ill<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſpoſition of the godly; vet they proceed alſo morally from this total forbearance of the Lords Supper, as a culpable and
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:115045:13"/>ſinful occaſion of them; whereas now on the other ſide, of the ſcandals in the wicked following upon adminiſtration of the Lords Supper, the adminiſtration of the Lords Supper is not a culpable and ſinful occaſion not <hi>occaſio data, ſed arrepta,</hi> not an occaſion ſinfully given, but ſinfully taken; even as ſin is occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioned by the Commandement, <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.11.13. So that they come therefrom only <hi>per accidens,</hi> and therefore may fitly be termed only accidentall ſcandals.</p>
            <p>I am willing to ſay all that I can in behalfe of them whom I oppoſe; And therefore I ſhall deſire you to conſider the ground why ſuch affirmative precepts, as command duties re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lating to others do not bind to alwaies. The duties that they command are principally to this end; That they do good to men for the curing of their evils,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Tombs</hi> of ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalizing. <hi>pag.</hi> 167, 168.</note> for the farthering of Vertue in them. Wherefore when Prudence ſheweth that ſuch acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons will be fruitleſſe in reſpect of the end, or contrariwiſe harmfull, they are to be forborne. But now the admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration of the Lords Supper is an un-Presbyterated Church is not only fruitleſſe, but harmfull unto the wicked; a Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter reacheth out unto them but their poiſon; they eat and drink their own damnation.</p>
            <p>For anſwer unto this. The great good and unſpeakable benefit that redounds to the Godly by adminiſtration of the Lords Supper, is a ſtronger, and more binding Argument for adminiſtring it, then the harme which comes unto the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked thereby; is for a totall forbearance, or ſeldome and rare adminiſtration thereof.</p>
            <p>To cleare this: Two things are to be proved.</p>
            <p>Firſt, That the great good, and unſpeakable benefit which redounds unto the godly by the adminiſtration of the Lords Supper is a convincing, and ſhould be a prevailing Argument for a Miniſter, to adminiſter it unto his ſtock; (notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the harme which comes unto the unworthy receivers) who intrude againſt the will both of the Miniſter, and the godly of his Congregation.</p>
            <p>Secondly, The harme which comes unto the wicked by the adminiſtration of the Lords Supper is a very weake, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſufficient Argument to conclude a totall forbearance, or a
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:115045:14"/>ſeldome adminiſtration of the Lords Supper to be warranta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble.</p>
            <p>The firſt is apparent from the end of the Lords Supper. Secondly, the duty of a Paſtor. Thirdly, the end of the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtorall Office.</p>
            <p>Firſt, Next unto God, and Chriſts glory, the good of the Saints was the maine end of this Sacrament: It was principal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly intended for the godly, for their uſe, comfort, and edifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, and therefore they are not to be deprived of it, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though it is much againſt their wils; accidentally prejudiciall unto wilfull and preſuptuous intruders.</p>
            <p>Secondly, the duty of a Paſtor is to feed the Church of God, which he hath purchaſed with his own bloud, with the food of the Sacrament, as well as the Word: <hi>Acts</hi> 20.28. Now we may do good to ſome, though evill by accident thereby redound to others without our default: Nay, we muſt do that good unto which our Calling obligeth us, let the iſſue or event of it unto others be what it will, or can be.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, The end of the Paſtoral Office is, as you may ſee <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.11, 12. <hi>for the perfecting of the Saints; for the edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying of the body of Chriſt;</hi> and therefore a Miniſter is di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligently and frequently to uſe all meanes which Chriſt hath inſtituted for this purpoſe: Of which the Lords Supper is one. Neither is he to forbeare the uſe of ſuch meanes, becauſe ſome without his fault and againſt his will, by their abuſe of them, contract guilt, and pull vengeance upon them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves.</p>
            <p>And this brings me unto the ſecond thing; That the harme which comes unto the wicked by the adminiſtration of the Lords Supper is a very weak and inſufficient Argument to conclude a totall forbearance, or ſeldome adminiſtration of the Lords Supper to be warrantable. And for this I ſhall give you theſe three reaſons, in which I ſhall preſuppoſe that which I have already proved in my clearing of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand.</p>
            <p>The firſt reaſon, Becauſe a Miniſter is not guilty of, nor acceſſory unto this harme which comes unto the wicked. For
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:115045:14"/>in adminiſtring the Lords Supper unto his flock, he doth but his duty, and we ſuppoſe beſides, that he hath done his utmoſt for prevention of their unworthy receiving.</p>
            <p>Secondly, A Miniſters totall forbearance, or a ſeldome adminiſtration of the Lords Supper is a culpable occaſion, and ſo conſequently a morall cauſe of the harme redounding unto the godly thereby; For it is a neglect of an Ordinance enjoyned by Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, if the accidental harme, which comes unto the unworthy receiver, can of it ſelf without ſome other ground, legitimate a neglect of adminiſtring the Lords Supper; then there can be no certaine Rule given when a Miniſter is to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſter the Lords Supper in any Church, whether Presbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated or un-Presbyterated. And indeed this plea of harme accrewing unto unworthy receivers by the Lords Supper, will hold as wel in a Presbyterated, as an un-Presbyterated Church. For if the Major part of Church-Officers be corrupt, ſcanda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous and unworthy receivers, may be tolerated, and ſo the Lords Supper may do them harme, not good. Shall the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter then wholly refrain from adminiſtring the Lords Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per? Unto this alſo you may adde, That ſcandalous perſons may be known to be ſuch unto the Miniſter, and yet he may not be able by ſufficient teſtimony to prove them to be ſo: In ſuch a caſe he knoweth, that theſe ſcandalous perſons will without a miracle eate and drinke their own judgement; and yet I hope you will not ſay, that for this he is to forbeare diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſation of the Lords Supper, untill their ſcandall can be detected, either by proofe, or their own confeſſion. And this of the firſt Argument. The Commandement we have for the adminiſtration of the Lords Supper. <hi>What if ſome did not beleeve</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle) <hi>Shall their unbeliefe make the faith of God without effect? Rom.</hi> 3.3. We may ſay, What if ſome receive the Lords Supper unworthily, ſhall their un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy receiving make the Lords Command for adminiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion thereof without effect?</p>
            <p>In a ſecond place we are to come to the Examples we have in Scripture for the adminiſtration of this Sacrament.
<note place="margin">The ſecond Argument <hi>ab] Exemplo.</hi>
               </note> Now there is not throughout the whole Scripture any one example
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:115045:15"/>of the Omiſſion of the Lords Supper in an un-Presbyterated Church. And therefore there can lye upon us no Obligation from example for omiſſion thereof. But we ſhall argue from Examples, not only negatively, but alſo affirmatively, and enquire what Patronage the adminiſtration of the Lords Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per in an un-Presbytera<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed Church hath from them.</p>
            <p>The firſt example that I ſhall inſtance in, ſhall be that of the firſt adminiſtration of the Lords Supper by our Saviovr, which was a patterne of all after-adminiſtrations, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore moſt exact and perfect in point of eſſentials. It wanted nothing eſſentially belonging unto the adminiſtration of the Lords Supper. Whereupon it is, that <hi>Paul</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.23. diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claimes all obtruding of additionals unto the Precept and Practiſe of our Saviour herein: <hi>I have received of the Lord</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>that which I delivered unto you.</hi> But now it was by Chriſt adminiſtred unto a Church which was not Presbytera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. (If we underſtand the Terme in regard of Ruling El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders.) And therefore to have Ruling Elders in a Church is not eſſential, but accidental unto the adminiſtration of the Lords Supper: And therefore the meere abſence or want of them (eſpecially when it is by the default of others only) is no ſufficient bar againſt adminiſtration of the Lords Supper. I confeſſe that we cannot conclude excluſively from Chriſts Example, That the Lords Supper ought to be adminiſtred on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in an un-Presbyterated Church; a Church void of Ruling Elders: no more then we can infer that it is only to be admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtred to men or Miniſters. But look, as becauſe Chriſt gave the Lords Supper only unto men; therefore it followeth, that it is lawfull to adminiſter the Lords Supper unto a Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion made up only of men; which is a thing uſuall in ſhips at Sea, and amongſt Merchants trading in remote parts: even ſo becauſe Chriſt gave the Lords Supper unto a Church deſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute of Ruling Elders; therefore the adminiſtration of it un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a Church that now is deſtitute of Ruling Elders is lawfull, as being agreeable unto the practice of Chriſt in the firſt ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtration thereof.</p>
            <p>A ſecond Example is in <hi>Acts</hi> 2.42. <hi>They continued ſted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faſtly in the Apoſtles Doctrine and Fellowſhip, and in break<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:115045:15"/>of bread, and in Prayers.</hi> The breaking of bread here mentioned, is not, ſay Interpreters, a common, but a Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred or Sacramentall breaking of bread. And Mr <hi>Shepheard</hi> in his Doctrine of the Sabbath <hi>Part.</hi> 2. <hi>pag.</hi> 23. gives a reaſon for it. The bread was no more common then the continuance in the Apoſtles Doctrine and fellowſhip was common. Now, that the Church was then Presbyterated is ſpoken gratis, without any colour from the Text. But you will ſay the Apoſtles were clothed with a fulneſſe of Juriſdiction. What if? Firſt, It is not ſaid, That the breaking of bread was by the Apoſtles only, or by their direction. And ſecondly, if it were: Did they act under the Notion of Apoſtles, extraordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Miniſters, or elſe as ordinary Miniſters? For the former, no Argument appeares in the Text, and for the latter, we have at leaſt a probable Argument. A Connexis, The Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine or Preaching, and the Prayers there mentioned belong to the Apoſtles as Miniſters, why not ſo alſo the breaking of bread?</p>
            <p>A third Example is <hi>Acts</hi> 20.7. And upon the firſt day of the week, when the Diſciples came together to break bread. From this Example thus I argue. The Lords day and all du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties belonging thereunto are to be obſerved even in Un-Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterated Churches; But the adminiſtration of the Lords Supper is a principall duty belonging to the Lords day: For Saint <hi>Luke</hi> deſcribes therefrom, as its end; the Aſſembly of the Diſciples upon that day, the firſt day of the week when the Diſciples came together to break bread. And it were ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurd to deſcribe a thing, as from its end, by that which is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neceſſary and leſſe principall. It were abſurd to deſcribe a conſtant meeting upon ſuch a day, as from its end, by that which is unuſuall upon the day. The evidence of this Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument is acknowledged by the <hi>London</hi> Divines in their Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Right of Church Government, <hi>Pag.</hi> 20, 21. Whatſoever actions were done by Saints recorded in Scripture, upon ſuch grounds as are of a morall, perpetual, and common concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to one perſon as well as another, to one Church as well as another; Theſe actions are obligatory to all, &amp; a rule to after generations; and for an inſtance they bring the Text now under
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:115045:16"/>debate. Thus, ſay they, the Churches practice of Preaching the Word, and breaking Bread on the firſt day of the week, <hi>Acts</hi> 20.7. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> is our rule for ſanctifying the Lords day, by celebrating the Word, Sacraments, and other holy Ordinances at theſe times. Unto whom we may adde Mr <hi>Shepheard</hi> in his Doctrine of the Sabbath <hi>Part.</hi> 2. <hi>pag.</hi> 22, 23. Here the breaking of bread is made mention of as the <hi>opus diei;</hi> or the eſpeciall buſineſſe of the day; and the day is mentioned as the eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all time for ſuch a purpoſe. And therefore it is called in effect the day of meeting to break bread. Holy duties are here cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led breaking of bread by a Synecdoche of a part for the whole, and therefore comprehends all other Sabbath duties. For there is no more reaſon to exclude Prayer, Preaching, ſinging of Pſalmes, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Becauſe theſe are not mentioned, then to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude drinking of wine in the Sacrament: (as the blind Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts do) becauſe this neither is here made mention of. Thus Mr <hi>Shepheard.</hi> But now we could not well take breaking of bread Synecdochycally for all Sabbath duties, unleſſe it were a principall part of them. If we conſult Eccleſiaſticall Stories, they informe us that the Lords Supper was adminiſtred every Lords day. <hi>Paraeus</hi> proves as much out of <hi>Juſtin Martyr</hi> and <hi>Tertullian.</hi> Indeed there be many who affirme that the Lords Supper was celebrated by the Primitive Chriſtians every day: But this ſtrengthneth my Argument, as is well collected by <hi>Nathaniel Eaton</hi> in his diſputation at <hi>Franeker,</hi> under the Moderation of Doctor <hi>Ames, de Sabbato &amp; die Dominico.</hi> If the Lords Supper were daily adminiſtred in the Primitive Church, why then is there particular mention made of the celebration of it on the firſt day of the week? unleſſe it be for the ſingular eminency of this day above others; and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe Chriſtians were bound by neceſſity of Command unto performance of this duty of celebrating the Lords Supper up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that day, whereas in other daies they were left unto their liberty.</p>
            <p>The fourth and laſt Example is in the Church of <hi>Corinth,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. And how ſtrongly concluſive this Example is for the adminiſtration of the Lords Supper in an Un-Presbytera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Church you ſhall heare, when we come to a Compariſon
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:115045:16"/>of an Un-Presbyterated Church, with a Presbyterated Church; in which there is a Mal-adminiſtration of Diſcipline: Unto which head we ſhall refer the conſideration of this Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple.</p>
            <p>The third principal Argument is taken from the general nature of the Lords Supper. It is an Ordinance of Chriſt,
<note place="margin">The third Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument, <hi>a ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nere.</hi>
               </note> one of thoſe myſteries of God which we read of 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.1, 2. A principall branch of Gods poſitive and inſtituted Worſhip; a part of that Profeſſion of faith which is required at our hands; And therefore to be adminiſtred even in an Un-Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terated Church.</p>
            <p>Firſt, the Ordinances of Chriſt may, nay, muſt be diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed even in an Un-Presbyterated Church, unleſſe there be ſome diſpenſation to the contrary; For they are under a Command, have promiſes annexed, are appointed for Gods honour, and our good: In the uſe of them we draw nigh un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God, and therefore omiſſion of them muſt needs be tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion, if we may diſpenſe them without ſin, for it is a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracting the ſhoulder from Gods burden, a neglecting an op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity to glorifie God, and ſo a ſin againſt God and our ſelves. But now the Lords Supper is an ordinance of Chriſt, and Miniſters have no diſpenſation in Scripture to omit the adminiſtration thereof. <hi>Ergo, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, Miniſters are to diſpenſe the myſteries of God without any exception, that we read of, as well in an Un-Presbyterated, as a Presbyterated Church, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.1, 2. <hi>Let a man ſo account of us, as of the Miniſters of Chriſt, and Stewards of the myſteries of God. Moreover, it is required in Stewards that a man be found faithfull;</hi> but the Lords Supper is a part of theſe myſteries. <hi>Ergo, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, no principal part of Gods poſitive and inſtituted Worſhip is to be omitted in an Un-Presbyterated Church; But the Lords Supper is a principal part of Gods poſitive, and inſtituted Worſhip. <hi>Ergo, &amp;c.</hi> The Minor is apparent out of what the incomparably learned <hi>Ameſius</hi> ſaith, <hi>Lib.</hi> 2. <hi>Theol. c.</hi> 13. <hi>Num.</hi> 17.18. The meanes which God hath ordained in this kind; ſome of them do propperly and immediately make to the exerciſing and furthering of faith, hope, and
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:115045:17"/>charity; as publike and ſolemn Preaching of the Word, celebration of Baptiſme, and the Lords Supper, and Prayer. And ſome of them are meanes for the right performance of theſe former, as the combination of the faithful into certain Congregations or Churches, Election, Ordination, and Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtration of Miniſters ordained by God, together with the care of Eccleſiaſtical diſcipline.</p>
            <p>Thoſe former are moſt properly the inſtituted Worſhip of God.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, No Sacraments of the New Teſtament are alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether to be forborn, omitted in an un-Presbyterated Church. But the Lords Supper is a Sacrament of the New Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament. <hi>Ergo, &amp;c.</hi> The major is thus confirmed. Nothing neceſſary to ſalvation, both by the neceſſity of Gods Command and as an ordinary means of ſalvation, is to be wholly and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together omitted; But all Sacraments of the New Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment are neceſſary to ſalvation, both by neceſſity of command and as ordinary means of ſalvation, <hi>Ergo, &amp;c.</hi> The minor is granted by all Proteſtants diſputing againſt Papiſts, for maintaining the abſolute neceſſity of baptiſme; they all yield that not only Baptiſme, but the Lords Supper alſo is neceſſary, <hi>neceſſitate tum Praecepti, tum medii ordinarii;</hi> as commanded duties, and as ordinary means of ſalvation, not of the purchaſe, but of the application of ſalvation. For they are ſeals aſſuring a beleever of his ſalvation; they are powerful Provocations unto holineſſe, which is the way unto ſalvation; they ſerve for the nouriſhment and increaſe of all our graces, and therefore they may be ſaid to be inſtrumental in the bringing us unto ſalvation it ſelfe; for by our graces and the exerciſe of them an entrance ſhall be miniſtred unto us abundantly, into the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verlaſting Kingdom of our Lord &amp; Saviour Jeſus Chriſt, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1 11. See <hi>Whittaker Praelect. de Sacrament is in genere. Quaeſt.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 1.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, a Profeſſion of faith in Chriſt may lawfully be made in an un-Presbyterated Church, not only verbally, but alſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally, by obſervation of ſuch ordinances as ſerve thereunto, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt which the Lords Supper may be reckoned one of the chief, for by it we ſhew forth the Lords death. We declare and witneſſe before all the world, that we owne and are not
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:115045:17"/>aſhamed of a crucified Chriſt; though unto the Jews a ſtum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling block, and unto the Greeks fooliſhneſſe: that we em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace the faith, doctrine and worſhip of Chriſt, and that we utterly renounce all idolatrous worſhip whatſoever, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.21. By it we profeſſe that our expectancy of righteouſneſſe and ſalvation, is grounded only upon the ſatisfaction and me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits of Chriſts death and ſufferings.</p>
            <p>I ſhall deſire all that are otherwiſe mind ed, then I am in this controverſie, ſeriouſly, and ſadly to reflect upon theſe fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentioned general attributions of the Lords Supper, and then to tell me with what warrant they neglect themſelves, and withhold from others an Ordinance of Chriſt? becauſe o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers the wicked abuſe and prophane it. Becauſe they who keep aloof from God in their lives, approach his Table; will they therefore refuſe to draw nigh unto God in the uſe of this holy and heavenly ordinance? how can they be accounted faithful ſtewards of the myſteries of God, who refuſe to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence unto Gods People a principal part of theſe myſteries, Bread and Wine in the Lords Supper? becauſe others worſhip him amiſſe, will they not therefore worſhip him at all? be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe others do not ſanctifie Gods name, but rather diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour him by their unworthy receiving, will they therefore rob God of his honour by neglecting ſo neceſſary a part of his Worſhip? will they wholly omit an ordinary means of ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, becauſe ſome by accident therein eat and drink damnati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on? Laſtly, will they forbear to make Profeſſion of their faith in the death of Chriſt, by receiving the ſigne, and pledge thereof, only becauſe ſome without their fault will joyne with them in making that Profeſſion, who in works deny Chriſt?</p>
            <p>A fourth principal Argument is taken from the inſtrumen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal cauſe of the adminiſtration of the Lords Supper. <hi>viz.</hi> The Miniſters of the Goſpel, and the power which they have as Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters to adminiſter the Lords Supper. It is called by Divines <hi>Poteſtas ordinis</hi> or <hi>Poteſtas muneris ſpecialis:</hi> and by the <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don</hi> Divines in their <hi>Divine right of Church-Government,</hi> is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fined to be a Church-power more ſpeciall, and particular to the office of ſome Church-governours only, as the power of
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:115045:18"/>preaching the Coſpel, &amp; which they as Miniſters may execute <hi>virtute officii:</hi> and it is diſtinguiſhed from the power of Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſdiction which is more general and common to the office of all Church-governours, as the power of Cenſures, wherein Ruling-Elders may act with Miniſters. Now from this their definition of the power of order, I thus argue. The power of order may be exerciſed in an un-Presbyterated Church: <hi>Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go</hi> the power of diſpenſing the Sacrament.</p>
            <p>The Argument follows <hi>à toto ad partes.</hi> For power to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpenſe the Sacraments, is a part or branch of the power of or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der. The conſequence then is undeniable. And as for the Antecedent, that may be confirmed by the above-mentioned deſcription of the power of order. That power which is on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly committed to the Miniſters of the Goſpel, and which they as Miniſters may execute <hi>virtute officii;</hi> that power may be executed in an un-Presbyterated Church, <hi>i. e.</hi> A Church deſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute of Ruling-Elders; But ſuch is the power of order, <hi>Ergo, &amp;c.</hi> That which belongs to Miniſters as Miniſters, belongs to all Miniſters, and always, in all ſtates and conditions of the Church, as well in an un-Presbyterated as a Presbyterated Church. For <hi>à quatenus ad de omni valet Argumentum:</hi> and the univerſality required in a Propoſition, that is, <hi>de omni,</hi> is <hi>uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſalitas Poſterioriſtica,</hi> as well as <hi>Prtoriſtica; Temporis,</hi> as well as <hi>Subjecti;</hi> Indeed this univerſality of time, this always is not to be underſtood, as in natural attributions, for that which is abſolutely ſuch in a mathematical latitude, but is to be taken (as uſually it is) when it is applyed to matters mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, for frequency or uſualneſſe. But ſome ſay, that however the power of order belong to a Miniſter in an un-Presbytera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Church wholly and entirely; yet he can then exerciſe but a part of this power, power of preaching the Word and baptizing; he cannot at all exerciſe the power of adminiſtring the Lords Supper. But this is ſpoken very unreaſonably and groundleſly, unleſſe in an un-Presbyterated Church, there be ſome impediment, that by Gods Word, or ſound reaſon is a ſufficient ground for non-adminiſtration of the Lords Supper: or unleſſe the adminiſtration of the Lords Supper preſuppoſe, as a neceſſary antecedent; a condition that dependeth upon
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:115045:18"/>the Elderſhip, and not upon the Miniſter only. For firſt eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry power is for its act, and therefore power in a Miniſter of adminiſtring the Lords Supper is not to lie idle and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>active; but to be exerciſed and actuated as often as there is a fit occaſion and opportunity; unleſſe there be ſome ſuch impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diment, as I ſpake of but now, &amp;c. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>Hoc eſt fru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtra, quod ſua natura in alterius gratiam est comparatum, quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do non perficit id, cujus gratia eſt, &amp; natura comparatum eſt. Ariſt. lib.</hi> 2. <hi>Phyſ. Text</hi> 62. Now if that may be ſaid in vaine which doth not reach that end, unto which it was ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed, much more may that be ſaid ſo, which is never uſed or applyed for the compaſſing of that end. Secondly, The edification of the Church of Chriſt is, as the <hi>London</hi> Divines ſay well, that eminent ſcope and end why Chriſt gave Church Government, and all other Ordinances of the New Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to the Church, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.8. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.10. The power then both of Order and Juriſdiction are both to be employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the edification of the Church. The power of Juriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction the Miniſter cannot exerciſe ſingly by himſelf, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out other Church Officers. The power of Order he may: For he alone is the ſeat and receptacle thereof. And what is uſually ſaid of the power of Order in generall may be affirm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of the power of adminiſtring the Lords Supper in parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular; if there be any thing that varies the caſe in this branch of the power of Order, let them produce it, and prove it, and I have done. Now a Miniſter ought to exerciſe and em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy for the edification of the Church all the power and au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority that he may lawfully exerciſe. For, not to employ it, were with the ſlothful ſervant in the Parable to hide his Talent in the earth. But now according to this opinion which we oppoſe; If the Church ſhould chance not to be Presbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated for a mans whole life, then a Miniſter is bound during that ſpace to ſuffer a branch of that power of Order which is ſeated ſingly in himſelf, to be idle and unactive all his life, and never to be exerciſed for the good, and edification of the Church.</p>
            <p>To avoid the dint of this Argument, they whom we oppoſe
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:115045:19"/>diſtinguiſh between Adminiſtration of, and admiſſion unto the Lords Supper. Adminiſtration of the Lords Supper they confeſſe a branch of the power of Order, and only belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to Miniſters: But admiſſion to the Lords Supper is, ſay they, an act of the power of Juriſdiction, and belongs not <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niſed <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nitati,</hi> to the Elderſhip. For they only are to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit who exclude. Now they ſay, this Admiſſion is a neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary Anticedent of this adminiſtration, and <hi>Negato Ante<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedente, neceſſario negabitur &amp; conſequen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi> In an Un-Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterated Church there can be no admiſſion, becauſe there is no Elderſhip. <hi>Ergo</hi> no adminiſtration.</p>
            <p>We diſtinguiſh of admiſſion: It is either negative or po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitive; negative, is nothing elſe but a non-hinderance; And though there be no Elderſhip, the Miniſter may not hinder thoſe whom he hath no power, I meane no lawfull authority to hinder. Now the Miniſter ſingly by himſelfe hath no Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority to hinder, keep back, or caſt out ſcandalous perſons: for ſo the power of Juriſdiction would be ſeated in him alone. But now ſecondly, There is an admiſſion that is poſitive, ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diciall, and implyeth a previous forenſicall examination by the Elderſhip, as of the parties admitted, ſo ſometimes of Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes, and Authoritative declaration of fitneſſe: And this is to be only in <hi>Collegio Presbyteriali,</hi> in the Colledge of Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byters, and Properly as they are in Court, but not <hi>ſeperatim,</hi> and out of Court. Now I conceive that this juridical and Authoritative admiſſion is not of abſolute neceſſity unto ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtration of the Lords Supper. By Baptiſme the Baptized are admitted or entered into the Church viſible, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.13. <hi>By one ſpirit we are all baptized into one body.</hi> See <hi>Rutherford</hi> in his due right of Presbyteries, <hi>p.</hi> 254. Now in ſome caſes the Lords Supper may be adminiſtred unto thoſe of yeares that are baptized without any new authoritative judiciall admiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Elderſhip.</p>
            <p>Firſt, This may be gathered from <hi>Acts</hi> 2.41, 42. Thoſe three thouſand ſoules whoſe Baptiſme is mentioned, <hi>verſe</hi> 41. have their receiving of the Lords Supper recorded, <hi>verſe</hi> 42. And there is not a word of any juridical admiſſion of them by the Elderſhip, coming between their Baptiſme, and their receiving of the Lords Supper.</p>
            <pb n="29" facs="tcp:115045:19"/>
            <p>Secondly, A perſecution may be ſo hot, as that it may ſcatter the Ruling Elders of a Church that they cannot con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vene in a ſpiritual Court to performe this juridicall admiſſion; and out of Court they have no Authoritative juriſdiction. May not now the Miniſter having a competent number of his flock, not yet admitted to the Sacrament, meeting him, who perhaps cannot ſtay long together for rage of the perſecuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on without apparent danger of their lives: May not now the Miniſter in ſuch a caſe for their conſolation adminiſter the Lords Supper to them? Nay, if they demand it, can he law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully withold it from them? And if in this caſe he may admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter it to them, then juridicall admiſſion is not a neceſſary Antecedent of adminiſtration.</p>
            <p>But becauſe this juridicall and authoritative admiſſion is inferred from the excluſion of groſly ignorant, and ſcanda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous perſons from the Lords Supper; we ſhall therefore en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire, whether or no this excluſion be a neceſſary Antecedent of the adminiſtration of the Lords Supper. And indeed if it be a neceſſary Antecedent thereof, it ſeemes undeniably to follow, that in an Un-Presbyterated Church, there can be no adminiſtration, becauſe no excluſion of the ſcandalous and groſly ignorant.</p>
            <p>For ſatisfaction to this we muſt diſtinguiſh of a neceſſary Antecedent. A thing may be ſaid to be a neceſſary Antece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent unto the adminiſtration of the Lords Supper, either by Morall, or Phyſicall obligation. That is a neceſſary Antece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent unto the Lords Supper by morall Obligation, that is morally required as a duty before the Lords Supper be admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtred: That is a neceſſary Antecedent unto the Lords Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per by Phyſicall obligation, which is eſſentially required for the Nature and Eſſence of the Lords Supper. The diſtinction though applyed to another purpoſe you may find at large ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained and applyed by <hi>Rutherford</hi> in his Peaceable Plea for <hi>Pauls</hi> Presbytery, <hi>cap</hi> 9. Now we grant that excluſion of groſly ignorant and ſcandalous perſons from the Lords Supper is morally required as a duty to go before the celebration of the Lords Supper. But of whom I pray is it required? You will ſay, not of the Miniſter ſingly, but of the whole Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery.
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:115045:20"/>Indeed it is required alſo of the people as a duty; that if they be Un-Presbyterated they do what lies in them for reformation of the condition of their Church, by a choice of ſuch Church Officers as are wanting. But what advantage do our Antagoniſts gaine by all theſe conceſſions? It is neceſſary, that is, commanded as a duty unto every Elderſhip to exclude the ſcandalous and groſly ignorant before the Lords Supper be adminiſtred; It is alſo neceſſary, that is, commanded to the People as a duty to labour Reformation by choice of Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling-Elders. But now it doth not follow from all this that it is neceſſary, that is, commanded as a duty to the Miniſter to for beare adminiſtration of the Lords Supper; if either the Elderſhip ſin in not excluding the unworthy; or the People ſin in not electing of Ruling Elders. The Elders ought to exclude the ſcandalous and groſly ignorant. The People ought to chuſe an Elderſhip before the Lords Supper be adminiſtred; and the Miniſter ought to forbeare the adminiſtration of the Lords Supper, in caſe either Elderſhip or people do not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme their duties, are three Propoſitions far wide: and he that can make good the inference of the laſt from the two firſt ſhall have ſuch credit with me, as that I will renounce <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> and learn a new Logick of him, without father ſtay then upon the firſt branch of the diſtinction; I ſhall only ſay thus much, That if the Elderſhip or People faile in their duty, it is no warrant for the Miniſter to omit his.</p>
            <p>But now perhaps they will ſay, That it is not the Miniſters duty to adminiſter the Lords Supper, but upon condition and preſuppoſal that the Elderſhip have performed theirs. To omit that this is ſpoken without any proofe, this aſſertion makes excluſion eſſentially required as an Antecedent of the adminiſtration of the Lords Supper abſolutely and indiſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſably neceſſary; Againſt which I ſhall oppoſe theſe following Arguments.</p>
            <p>Firſt, the Lords Supper is invalid and nul, that is, it cannot be at all without that which is eſſentially pre-required. Where there is wanting any eſſential pre-requiſite, the pretended acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is not the Lords Supper, but a nullity. In ſuch a caſe the actions and the Elements are not Sacramentall: But now
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:115045:20"/>the Lords Supper is not invalid and nul without this Exclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion; therefore this excluſion is not eſſentially pre-required to the Lords Supper.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Adminiſtration of the Lords Supper is a more important and neceſſary duty then excluſion, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> or any other part of the exerciſe of Diſcipline; for it is more properly and immediately the Worſhip of God then the exerciſe of diſcipline, as may be ſeen in the place before quoted out of <hi>Ames lib.</hi> 2. <hi>Theol cap.</hi> 13. <hi>n.</hi> 17, 18. God is more worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped by the adminiſtration of the Sacraments then by Church cenſures; The Sacraments are a principall Worſhip of God; Church cenſures and the exerciſe of Diſcipline leſſe principal. Now it is improbable that a leſſe principal Worſhip of God ſhould be a neceſſary Antecedent to a principal Worſhip. There is ſaith <hi>Rada, duplex ordo naturae; alius ordo eſſentialis dependen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentiae; alius eſt ordo eſſentialis eminentiae. &amp; perfectionis; qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis eſt inter excedens, &amp; exceſſum.</hi> Now excluſion (and we may ſay the like of all other acts of Diſcipline) is not before the Lords Supper in regard of the order, either of eſſential de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendency, or of eſſential eminency and perfection. The Lords Supper hath not an eſſentiall dependency upon exclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, or any other acts of Diſcipline: and it is in <hi>ratione cul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus</hi> of more eſſential eminency and perfection; as being more immediatly and properly the Worſhip of God. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is apparent that excluſion is not a neceſſary Antecedent to it. The omiſſion therefore of excluſion by others without our default is no ground for us to omit that which is a more important and neceſſary duty, and withall is in our power to performe.</p>
            <p>Againe, it is not probable that an ordinance which is more ſeperable from the Church then the Sacraments, ſhould be a neceſſary Antecedent to the adminiſtration of the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments: But the exerciſe of Diſcipline is more ſeparable from the Church then the Sacraments; as appeares by what our Divines write againſt the Papiſts touching the marks of the Church: <hi>Whittaker de Eccleſ controv.</hi> 2. <hi>Quaeſt.</hi> 5. <hi>cap.</hi> 17. as alſo againſt thoſe of the ſeperation. <hi>Rutherford</hi> in his due right of Presbytery, <hi>pag</hi> 287, 288, <hi>Whittaker</hi> in the forequoted place,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:115045:21"/>makes the adminiſtration of the Sacraments to be in ſome ſort and ſenſe an eſſential mark of the Church; withall he excludes Diſcipline from being ſo. The exerciſe of Diſcipline, ſaith <hi>Rutherford,</hi> is not neceſſary for the eſſence of a viſible Church, but only neceſſary to the well-being of a Church. But now, All do ſay, That the Sacraments are, though not abſolutely, yet in ſome degrees neceſſary to the eſſence and being of a Church. So then if you compare together theſe two duties, excluſion of ſcandalous and ignorant perſons from the Lords Supper, and the celebration of the Lords Supper. The Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligation unto the adminiſtration of the Lords Supper is of the two the greater and more weighty. For the Lords Supper is more the Worſhip of God, leſſe ſeparable from, and more neceſſary to the Church then excluſion of ſcandalous and groſly ignorant perſons from the Lords Supper: Therefore it is altogether improbable that this latter, <hi>(viz.)</hi> excluſion, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> ſhould be an Antecedent abſolutely neceſſary unto the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, <hi>(viz.)</hi> the celebration of the Lords Supper. Againe, Diſcipline and all branches of it are compared to a ſpiritual Rod, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.21. The Lords Supper is compared to ſpirituall food or bread; Now it is unlikely that a Rod ſhould be a ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary Antecedent to food or bread, that is, that children be kept without bread untill a Rod be provided to whip the dogs and ſwine.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, As the celebration of the Lords Supper is a more important duty then excluſion, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> or the exerciſe of any other branch of Diſcipline: So the Commandement for the celebration of the Lords Supper is more cleare, expreſſe, and evident then that for the exerciſe of Diſcipline. For the former is uncontroverted amongſt all ſave ſome Popiſh Schoolmen, whereas nothing can be more controverted then the latter. Witneſſe elſe thoſe endleſſe diſputes touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Diſcipline by the Prelatical party, Eraſtians, Presbyteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, Independents. Now if it be in doubtful matters the beſt way to take the ſafeſt courſe, I ſhould conclude, That a duty ſo wounderfully controverted is not an Antecedent abſolutely neceſſary unto that which is uncontroverted, by all generally granted to a duty.</p>
            <pb n="33" facs="tcp:115045:21"/>
            <p>Fourthly, In the abſence of the Ruling Elders of a perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Church, the Miniſter may lawfully adminiſter the Lords Supper unto the remainder of the ſcattered flock; though ſome Profeſſors, who deſerve excluſion be againſt the wils of the beſt affected joyned with them. The perſecution may be ſo hot, as that thoſe who ſtay behind, may every houre be in jeopardy for their lives, in danger to be haled unto a ſtake, and how their Miniſters, ſtaying with them, can in ſuch a caſe lawfully withold from them (aſſembling themſelves to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether to communicate in other Ordinances) that Sacrament which Chriſt hath appointed for the ſtrengthning, comfort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and confirming of his members; eſpecially when they begge, call, and cry for it; I profeſſe I cannot ſee.</p>
            <p>All theſe former Arguments receive weight and ſtrength from this conſideration; That the exerciſe of Diſcipline is not a neceſſary antecedent unto the exerciſe of other bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of the power of Order; to wit, the power of Preaching, Baptizing, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Therefore to ſay without proof, that it is a ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary antecedent unto the exerciſe only of this Branch, of the power of Order, is <hi>Petitio Principii,</hi> a meer begging of the <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The fifth Principal Argument is taken from the end of the Lords Supper.
<note place="margin">The 5. Arg. à fine.</note> The principall ends of the Lords Supper have place in, and do belong unto an Un-Presbyterated Church; and therefore likewiſe the Lords Supper it ſelf. The conſequence is made good from that Maxime in Logick, <hi>Poſito fine ponuntur omnia media ad finem;</hi> The Antecedent is mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt from an enumeration of the ends of the Lords Supper. It will be an endleſſe work to go over them all; I ſhall therefore out of them all ſelect two.</p>
            <p>The firſt is that which by Chriſts moſt expreſſe command is to be the end of this Sacrament; And it is to celebrate the memory of Chriſts Death and Paſſion, that unvaluable price of our double Redemption, Redemption from hell, and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption to glory: <hi>This do in remembrance of me.</hi> And doth it not become Chriſtians to celebrate with a frequent (ſhall I
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:115045:22"/>ſay) nay rather with an eternal memory the Author of their Redemption? Shall ſo great and glorious a work be buried in a grave of oblivion? And ſhall that (I mean the Lords Supper, which is by divine inſtitution, a Pledge and memorial of this ſo incomparable a mercy be neglected and quite thrown aſide, if the government of the Church by the iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the times be not ſetled in our times. Chriſts death is to be remembred with a memory, both of faith and gratitude; even in an Un-Presbyterated Church. Therefore the Lords Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per which was by Chriſt inſtituted for the commemoration thereof, is to be celebrated in an Un-Presbyterated Church.</p>
            <p>Secondly, I ſhall argue from another end of the Lords Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per: The ſpiritual growth and nouriſhment of Chriſtians. The Lords Supper is defined by <hi>Ames,</hi> to be the Sacrament of the nouriſhing, and growth of the faithful in Chriſt: Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon he inferres that it ought oftentimes to be adminiſtred to the ſame perſons.</p>
            <p>In an Un-Presbyterated Church Chriſtians ought to grow in grace, to nouriſh, and improve their graces all they can? Why then ſhould they be denyed that, which Chriſt himſelfe hath appointed, as an help and means of this growth and nouriſhment? Me thinks it is ſomewhat a ſtrange kind of rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoning, becauſe the rod of Diſcipline is wanting; the children ſhould be denyed bread; yea, but you will ſay, dogges will eat the childrens bread, Why, will you therefore ſtarve the children, becauſe dogges without your default may ſnatch the childrens portion? Shall the children be debarred (as I may ſay) their daily bread, becauſe it will become accidentally poyſon unto dogges? Hither may we referre theſe words of the <hi>Bramble Berrie.</hi> As it is better for Gods ſheep to feed upon paſture, where ſome weeds grow, rather then ſtarve for want of food: So it is better for Gods ſhepheards to ſuffer ſome weeds to grow in the ſheeps paſtures, if they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not prevent it, then to ſtarve their flocks; yea, and as it is bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter for the ſheep to feed among goats, rather then ſtarve: So it is better the ſhepheards ſhould ſuffer the goats to feed upon the ſheeps paſture, though it ſhould poyſon them, then for the
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:115045:22"/>ſheep to be kept from it; It being as I ſaid out of their power to reforme it. Hither you may referre that place of <hi>Becca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus. ſum. Theol. Part.</hi> 3. <hi>Tract.</hi> 2. <hi>Cap.</hi> 23. <hi>Queſt.</hi> 4. <hi>Hoc praeceptum divinum tum maxime obligat, cum prudenter judicatur Euchariſtiae ſumptionem, neceſſariam eſſe homini ad e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um finem, ob quem inſtituta eſt, nimirum ad conſervandam, &amp; roborandam vitam ſpiritualem contra tentationes. Ratio eſt, quia hoc eſt commune Praeceptis affirmativis, ut tunc obligent, quando urget neceſſitas finis, propter quem inſtituta ſunt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſixt Argument is drawn from the Object of the admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtration of the Lords Supper,
<note place="margin">The ſixth Argument. <hi>Ab Objecto.</hi>
               </note> ſuch as have theſe qualificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons which the Scripture requireth, in thoſe to whom it is to be adminiſtred, and theſe qualifications are eſpecially two. Firſt, Right unto; Secondly, Need of the Lords Supper. Now in an Un-Presbyterated Church, there are ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny who have right unto, and need of the Lords Supper; why then ſhould it be with-held from them? Becauſe they have right unto it, the Miniſter is tyed to give it them by an obligation of juſtice; becauſe they have need of it, the Miniſter is bound to give it them, by an obligation of cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity.</p>
            <p>Firſt, Many have right unto it, not only <hi>jus adrem,</hi> but alſo <hi>jus in re;</hi> not only a right in <hi>actu primo,</hi> but alſo a right in <hi>actu ſecundo;</hi> which rendreth the perſon actually and preſently capable of the thing that he is intituled to. That which giveth ſuch a right in <hi>Foro Dei,</hi> is Eaith; but in <hi>Foro Eccleſiaſtico,</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of the Faith. Now in an Un-Presbyterated Church, there are many who are Beleevers, and Profeſſors of the Faith: <hi>Ego,</hi> many that have right unto the Lords Supper. And we may argue from the right to the adminiſtration. <hi>Philip</hi> did ſo to the <hi>Eunuch</hi> in caſe of Baptiſme. The <hi>Eunuch</hi> ſaid <hi>here is water, what doth hinder me to be baptized?</hi> And <hi>Philip</hi> ſaid, <hi>If thou beleeveſt withall thine heart, thou mayſt.</hi> So may we ſay; here is bread and wine, &amp;c. <hi>Peter</hi> alſo thus reaſoneth, <hi>Acts</hi> 10.47. <hi>Can any forbid water, that theſe ſhould not be baptized, which have received the Holy Ghoſt as well as we?</hi> So may we ſay, can any man forbid bread and wine, that theſe
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:115045:23"/>ſhould not receive the Lords Supper, which have received the Holy Ghoſt; and have in ſome degree all ſpirituall qualifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions requiſite in Communicants. They have the word of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> which is the greater; who can inhibit the ſigne which is the leſſe? They are M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Geree</hi> his words for the Baptiſme of Infants. They are <hi>faederati,</hi> therefore they muſt be <hi>ſignati.</hi> It is M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Marſhals</hi> argument upon the ſame ſubject; and <hi>mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatis mutandis</hi> applyable to our purpoſe. Perhaps you will ſay, you would willingly give Beleevers their right; but prophane and ſcandalous perſons will alſo intrude who have no right: What if they do? If you have no power or authority from Chriſt to keep them back by your ſelf; If you have uſed the utmoſt of your power to erect an Elderſhip in the Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation; if you have uſed your power of Order to the utmoſt for keeping them back by exhortation, if you mourne for their intruſion, wherein are you to be blamed? Becauſe they do wrong, will you do no right? And ſhall the Saints be debarred their dues, becauſe theſe wretches without your allowance, ſeiſe upon what is undue, that unto which they have no right? I ſhall conclude this Argument with that of the Bramble Berry. As it were better in our almes to relieve ten Counterfeits, then let Chriſt go naked and hungry in any one member: So it were better to admit ten Hypocrites to the Table of the Lord, then deprive one Godly man of this ſoul nouriſhment.</p>
            <p>To this Argument we may adde weight by conſidering, that in an Un-Presbyterated Church; Beleevers have not only a right to the Lords Supper, but alſo need of it. Their own ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſities (ſaith Mr. <hi>Pemble</hi>) may perſwade them to frequent celebration of this Sacrament, if they can be ſenſible of their ſpiritual weakneſſe and wants. Let them look inward and ſee how great need they have of many and often confirmations of their faith, renovations of their repentance, of ſtirring up the graces of God in the ſoul, to adde an edge and eagerneſſe to all ſpiritual affections after holineſſe, to get unto themſelves the moſt powerful provocations unto obedience: Every one that hath grace, knows how frequently the power thereof is impared by temptations, weakned by worldly diſtractions,
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:115045:23"/>even of our lawful employments, and overmaſtered by the force of ſinful luſts; ſo that they muſt needs diſcover a great deal of ignorance in their ſpiritual eſtate, that feel not in their ſoules a proneneſſe to a famiſhment, as well as in their bodies; at leaſt they bewray intolerable carleſneſſe, that finding the emptineſſe and leanneſſe of their ſouls; yet neglect to repaire often unto this holy Table, whereon is ſet forth the bread of life; whereof when they have eaten, their ſpirit may come again, their hearts may be ſtrengthned, their ſouls may be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleniſhed as with marrow and fatneſſe.</p>
            <p>The Miniſters and Elders met together in the late Provinci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all Aſſembly at <hi>London</hi> in their Vindication of the Presbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riall Government, conſider the Sacrament under a four fold Notion.</p>
            <p>Firſt, As it is a ſpirituall medicine to cure the remainders of our corruption.</p>
            <p>Secondly, As it is ſpirituall food to ſtrengthen our weak graces.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, As it is a ſpirituall cordiall to comfort our diſtreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed conſciences.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, As it is a ſtrong obligation, and forcible engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to all acts of thankfulneſſe and obedience unto Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Now Beleevers in an Un-Presbyterated Church, have need of the Lords Supper under all theſe conſiderations.</p>
            <p>Firſt, Their ſouls are perpetually diſeaſed, and therefore they ſtand in need of the frequent uſe of this Sacrament, as a ſoveraigne medicine to heal them.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Their ſouls are naturally empty of all ſpirituall goodneſſe, their graces feeble and defective; their faith weak and often ſtaggering, their hope fainting, their love cold, their zeal languiſhing. And therefore the Lords Supper is frequently needful, as ſpiritual food for the nouriſhing and ſtrengthening of all their graces; for the confirming of their faith, quickning of their hope, rowzing of their love, and kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of their zeal. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, The faith of the ſtrongeſt Beleevers may be ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, their aſſurance ecclipſed with doubts, their ſpirituall joy
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:115045:24"/>darkned with fears, diſcomforts and afflictions. They may walk in darkneſſe and ſee no light. And in ſuch a caſe the Lords Supper is neceſſary, as a precious Cordiall to revive and chear up their ſinking ſpirits, to confirme their doubting, and to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort their diſtreſſed conſciences.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, The hearts of the beſt of men are falſe and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteadfaſt, looſe and deceitfull, apt to ſtart from God and his juſt commands. They therefore want the Lords Supper for renuall of their Covenant with God; that ſo thereby they may bind, faſten and engage themſelves a freſh unto God in the ſtrength of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>The ſeventh Argument is from compariſon of the Lords Supper with Baptiſme.
<note place="margin">The ſeventh Argument, <hi>A Comparatis.</hi>
               </note> It is a generally received Maxime amongſt Divines, that Baptiſme ought to be adminiſtred but once, for it is the ſeal of our new birth, and we are borne but once. The Lords Supper ought to be adminiſtred often, for we ſtand in need continually of food, nouriſhment, confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Now by this Divinity, that the Lords Supper is not to be adminiſtred in an Un-Presbyterated Church, it will follow: That if the Church wherein we live be not all our lives long Presbyterated, that then in ſuch a condition of the Church, Baptiſme is to be adminiſtred once, the Lords Supper never.</p>
            <p>The eight Argument is drawn from the conſideration of the oppoſite of the adminiſtration of the Lords Supper;
<note place="margin">The eight Argument <hi>Ab Oppoſito.</hi>
               </note> the non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>adminiſtration thereof. Non-adminiſtration of the Lords Supper in an Un-Presbyterated Church is unlawful; There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore adminiſtration in an Un-Presbyterated Church is lawful. That non-adminiſtration of the Lords Supper (I mean thereby at otal forbearance of the adminiſtration therefore) is unlawful in an Un-Presbyterated Church, I prove by theſe three follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Arguments.</p>
            <p>All unwritten Traditions in matters of Worſhip and Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion are unlawful: But a totall forbearance of the admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration of the Lords Supper in an Un Presbyterated Church is an unwritten Tradition, having no precept, or exmaple in Scripture to countenance it: <hi>Ergo, &amp;c.</hi> There is expreſſe Scripture for adminiſtration of the Lords Supper unto the
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:115045:24"/>Churches of God. As for the reſtriction of it unto Presbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated Churches, it cannot be made good from Scripture. And Commentaries, Expoſitions of Scripture that are not by good conſequence deducible therefrom, are unwritten Traditions, and humane Preſumptions. However we cannot argue nega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tively from humane teſtimonies, we may yet from divine the Scriptures. For they are able to make a man wiſe unto ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and throughly to furniſh the man of God (a Miniſter) to all good works; able to give him ſufficient direction, when to performe, when to omit duties. And therefore ſeeing there is ſuch a deep ſilence in the Scriptures, concerning the totall forbearance of adminiſtring the Lords Supper in an Un-Presbyterated Church; I cannot but conclude it to be unneceſſary. The Lord may ſay unto us, who hath required this at your hand. Theſe two things differ wide.</p>
            <p>Firſt, Scandalous perſons ought to be excluded the Lords Supper.</p>
            <p>Secondly, If for want of an Elderſhip they cannot be exclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, therefore we muſt wholly forbear adminiſtration of the Lords Supper. The former is obvious in Scripture, the latter an unwritten Tradition.</p>
            <p>But you will ſay there is warrant for Omiſſion of the Lords Supper, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> The Paſſe over was omitted by the Children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> in the Wilderneſſe, as alſo circumciſion: whence we may argue by way of Analogy and Proportion for Omiſſion of the Lords Supper; when the Church is in a Wilderneſſe, and if ever ſhe were in a Wilderneſſe, then now.</p>
            <p>Firſt, Arguments from meer and naked Analogy and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion, without ſome other ground are not concludent; o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe we might argue for a Pope from the Jews High-Prieſt. But as to the inſtances I wonder, why omiſſion of the Paſſeoves in the Wilderneſſe is alledged For after the firſt cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bration thereof, all future celebrations were by expreſſe &amp; plain command to be only in the land of <hi>Canaan,</hi> Exod. 13.4, 5. &amp;c. Deut. 16. from verſe 1. <hi>uſque ad</hi> 8. <hi>Rivet.</hi> upon <hi>Exodus. verſ.</hi> 5. clears this very well, whoſe words I ſhall take leave to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſert. <hi>Moſes declarat quo tempore ſolemnitatis illius celebrat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o inchoari debeat: nempe poſt introductionem Populi, in terra pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribus
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:115045:25"/>promiſſa; Tum (inquit) coles, Deum nempe, iſto cultu, in iſto menſe, non in deſerto, ſed in terrâ patribus tuis promiſſâ; Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſſe videtur, tot populorum, ut oppoſitâ promiſſione &amp; potentiâ Dei, eos muniret adverſus tentationem diffidentiae, quae obrepere potuiſſet, ſi ſimpliciter conſideraſſent, quàm arduum eſſet negoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um, tot nationes &amp; ſuis ſedibus deturbare. At inquit Moſes, res adeo certa eſt, ut Deus cultum illum à vobis non requirat, quem nunc praeſcribit; niſi poſtquam promiſſum illudſuum impleverit. Hinc ergo apparet legem comedendi agnum, ut azymes panes, non obligaſſe Iſraelitas totis</hi> XL. <hi>annis, quibus vagabuntur in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerto inſtabiles, &amp; rebus omnibus incompoſitis. Quod de pleriſque ſtatutis dicendum eſt, quae poſtea Deus per Moſem evulgavit, ut liquet, ex</hi> Deut. 12. verſ. 1. <hi>Haec ſunt illa ſtatuta &amp; judicia, quae obſervanter facturi eſtis in illâ terrâ, quam dat Deus majo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum tuorum tibi ut haereditario poſſideas eam, omnibus diebus quibus victuri eſtis ſuper terram. Antea enim quod ad oblationes, &amp; ſimilia attinebat, non potuit uſque adeo in ambulatoriis Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raelitarum caſtris obſervari, aut ſummo jure ab illis exigi: quod ſtatutum erat, quo tempore etiam indultum eſt illis ut incircum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſi manerent. Hoc indicat Moſes,</hi> ver. 8, 9. <hi>Non facietis ſecun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum omnia quae facimus hodie, quiſque quicquid videtur rectum in oculis ſuis: non adhuc enim ingreſſieſtis ad locum illum quietis, &amp; ad poſſeſſionem illam, quam Iehova dat tibi, &amp;c. Et certe non poterat Azymoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſolemnitas ſervari, uti cum manna veſcerentur, nullus erit uſus fermenti cum triticeo pane, non veſcerentur. Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mode itaque haec declaratio annexa est, ne ſcrupulum aliquem conſcientiis injiceret mandati illius omiſſio ſpacio anno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum,</hi> XL.</p>
            <p>As for Circumciſion, I demand whether their omiſſion of it were with leave from God, or without leave? if without leave, then it was ſinful, and ſo no Plea for the non-admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration of the Lords Supper: if it were with leave, then it was either by ſpecial and extraordinary Revelation from God; or by ſome general rule and direction contained in the written law, or law of nature; if by eſpecial and extraordinary Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velation, ſhew ſome ſuch warrant for forbearance of the Lords Supper, and I have done; if by ſome general rule and direction contained either in the written law, or law of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:115045:25"/>produce that rule and direction, &amp; apply it to the preſent forbearance of the Lords Supper, &amp; the controverſie is at end.</p>
            <p>A ſecond Argument; a negative ſeparation, that is, a non-Communion with the Church in a lawful and comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded worſhip is unlawful; Therefore alſo a total forbearance of the adminiſtration of the Lords Supper in an un-Presbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated Church is unlawful. For the antecedent I ſhall referre you to all that write againſt the ſeparation, who generally diſtinguiſh ſeparation into Negative and Poſitive; Negative, is a non-Communion in Ordinances. Poſitive, when we gather and grow into another body, and they codclude them both to be unlawful. The conſequent will be evident, if you pleaſe to read thoſe who have written againſt the ſeparation; for you will find that many of their Arguments <hi>mutatis mutandis,</hi> may be ſadled againſt this forbearance of the Lords Supper. I ſhall therefore deſire you to make tryal of this for proofe of this Argument; And after you have made ſuch tryall, you will, I beleeve, conclude non-adminiſtration to be a greater evil then ſeparation, becauſe the Miniſter thereby not only neglects himſelf an Ordinance of God, but alſo keeps all others from it.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, it is unlawful for a Miniſter by himſelf to excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate ſo much as one member of his Church, with that which Divines call the leſſer excommunication, which is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion from the Lords Supper; therefore his total forbear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of the adminiſtration of the Lords Supper in an un-Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterated Church is unlawful. The Antecedent wil not at all be denyed by thoſe whom I oppoſe; for the Miniſter by him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to exclude judicially from the Lords Supper, what were it but to lord it over Gods heritage? ſole power of Iuriſdiction, Chriſt hath vouchſafed to no one Perſon on earth; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Papal and Prelatical, for being ſo, hath been cenſured by the Orthodox to be unlawful and Antichriſtian. As for the conſequence or ſequel that is apparent; becauſe a Miniſter by a total forbearance of the adminiſtration of the Lords Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, doth exclude his whole Church from the Lords Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per. And therefore his non-adminiſtration of the Lords Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, is a virtual Excommunication. Now we may argue from the leſſe to the greater thus. If it be unlawful for a Miniſter to
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:115045:26"/>exclude by himſelf, one member from the Lords Supper, when he celebrates it; it is much more unlawful for him to exclude the whole Church, by refuſal to celebrate it, if he cannot de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barre one Communicant; how lies it in his power to diſ-com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon a whole Church? if a ſteward wrong one ſervant by thruſting him from the Table without Authority &amp; Commiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on from his Lord; doth he not much more wrong the whole fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily, if he withhold from them meat and drink, and will not let them have their conſtant meals allowed them by their ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter? Neither is the matter any whit mended by ſaying, that there is a difference between an excluſion from the Lords Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per by poſitive and formal excommunication, and that exclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion which is by non-adminiſtration; For it is unlawful to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude from the Lords Supper by a ſinful omiſſion or neglect of the exerciſe of the power of order, which is ſeated only in the Miniſter, as well as it is unlawful to exclude from the Lords Supper, by an unjuſt uſurpation of ſole power of Iuriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction, that belongs to the whole Elderſhip.</p>
            <p>And let this ſuffice for the firſt ſort of Arguments drawne from the Lords Supper, and the admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration thereof.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>
               <hi>A ſecond ſort of Arguments in which I will be brief, may be taken from the other terme conſiderable in the queſtion, a Non-Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terated Church.</hi> i.e. <hi>A Church deſtitute of Ruling-Elders.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <hi>And here we may argue</hi> à Genere, ab Exem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plo, à Comparatis.</p>
            <p>FRom the general nature of an un-Presbyterated Church Un-Presbyterated Churches,
<note place="margin">Firſt à Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nere, Cum in <hi>Abel,</hi> &amp; <hi>Cain,</hi> inci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peret diviſio civitatis ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tualis Hieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem, à civi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate Babylo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis, oportuit eſſe ſigna ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qua ſacra, qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus diſtingue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentur cives Hieruſalem, à civibus Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylonis: ſicut videmus in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liis rebus: o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ves enim uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us gregis, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernuntur ab ovibus alterius gregis, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prio ſigno; &amp; ſacrae aedes, à non ſacris, propriis ſignis diſcernuntur; &amp; civitas nobilis aliquo ſigno donati conſuevit: ut civitas Romana, pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nula: &amp; dignitas militaris accinctione gladii: &amp; oſſicium traditione virgae, vel clavi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um; ex quibus omnibus calligitur, quod Sacramenta fuerunt neceſſaria homini poſt lapſum, ad hoc ut diſcerneretur eſſe civis ſpiritualis Hieruſalem, &amp; de grege domini, es de militâ <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>jus. <hi>Alexand. Alenj. Par.</hi> 4. <hi>q.</hi> 1. <hi>m.</hi> 2. <hi>ar.</hi> 2.</note> (ſuch as our Churches gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally in <hi>England</hi>) are true Churches; and therefore ſhould have
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:115045:26"/>the marks of a true Church. Now adminiſtration of the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments hath been always counted amongſt the marks and ſignes of a true Church, by ſuch as have written concerning the marks of the Church againſt Papiſts, as alſo by the old non-Conformiſts writing againſt thoſe of the ſeparation. Many of them have gone ſo farre, as to reckon the Sacraments amongſt the eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſential notes of the Church. Which aſſertion is explicated the beſt and cleareſt by <hi>Ames,</hi> that ever I read in any. <hi>Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibentur iſtae notae</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>ſcilicet vera praedicatio Evangelii; legitima adminiſtratio Sacramentorum; &amp; legitima diſciplina non ad veram. Eccleſiam militantem, quoad eſſentiam ejus inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nam, certo &amp; neceſſario declarandam: ſed ut viſibilem aliquem coetum deſignandum, qui eſt Eccleſia particularis ex inſtituto Chriſti formata.</hi> But the Church ought to uſe theſe marks which God hath appointed, to diſtinguiſh her from the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panies of Infidels and Pagans, as alſo from the Aſſemblies of Antichriſt, though they be not ſimply eſſential and recipro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal. Mine Argument therefore ſtands in its full ſtrength, though the Lords Supper were not an eſſentiall mark of the Church.</p>
            <p>The ſecond Argument ſhall be taken from the example of an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>un-Presbyterated Church.
<note place="margin">Ab Exemplo.</note> Suppoſe divers Chriſtians of ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall Countryes, yet underſtanding one language, ſhould ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſually be together in ſome ſea town of <hi>Turky, Africa,</hi> &amp;c. de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitute of a conſtant miniſter; now ſuppoſe ſome godly Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter ſhould come on ſhore to them out of ſome ſhip, who on make no long ſtay with them; I would willingly know whether they may not receive the Lords Supper from him, and he adminiſter it to them; if they may, then we have one inſtance of an un-Presbyterated Church, capable of the admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtration of the Lords Supper. And the truth of an univerſal negative is overthrown by one particular affirmative. I might
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:115045:27"/>alſo inſtance in Churches under the extremity of perſecution, when the Saints have no conſtant abode, but are always in a wandring and flying poſture from city to city; though by the extream rage of the Perſecution, Churches un-Presbyterated have not opportunity to forme themſelves into a Presbytery; and in Churches Presbyterated, the Ruling-Elders are ſo ſcat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered, as that they cannot convene in an Eccleſiaſtical Court: ſhall the People of God now in ſuch a caſe be denied the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort of the Lords Supper? becauſe the world frowns on them, ſhall therefore the Pledges of Gods favour be denied unto them? what is this but to adde affliction to the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted?</p>
            <p>The laſt Argument ſtrikes againſt the only reaſon pretend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,
<note place="margin">The 3. Arg. <hi>à comparatis.</hi>
               </note> for forbearance of the adminiſtration of the Lords Supper in an un-Presbyterated Church, which is, becauſe ſcandalous Perſons cannot there be excluded from the Lords Supper. And it is taken from a compariſon of an un-Presbyterated Church, with ſuch a Presbyterated Church, wherein there is either neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect or mal-adminiſtration of diſcipline. It is drawn <hi>à ſimili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus,</hi> and built upon this maxime. <hi>Similium ſimilis eſt ratio, ſi ſimilia ſpectentur quâ talia ſunt, ſeu quatenus ſimilia ſunt, &amp; quoad illud tertium, in quo ſit comparatio.</hi> There is a likeneſſe as to the matter of ſinful mixtures, betwixt an un-Presbytera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and a Presbyterated Church, wherein there is either neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect or mal-adminiſtration of diſcipline. In ſuch a Church there will in all likelihood be ſinful mixtures, for we ſuppoſe the major part of Church-officers to be corrupt, and likely to give countenance to ſcandalous and wicked Perſons, to tole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate them in Church-Communion, to admit them unto the Lords Supper; but now for theſe mixtures the adminiſtrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Lords Supper is not to be forborn in a Presbytera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Church; therefore theſe mixtures are no ſufficient argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment againſt the adminiſtration of the Lords Supper in an un-Presbyterated Church. That the admiſſion of ſcandalous Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons to the Lords Supper in a Presbyterated Church, is no ground or warrant to forbear the adminiſtration thereof, may be made good by inſtancing in the Church of <hi>Corinth,</hi> where there were ſchiſmes and contentions; 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.12, 13. Envy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:115045:27"/>and ſtrife, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.3. An inceſtuous Perſon, not caſt out of Church-Communion, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. Going to law with the bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren before infidels, eating at the idols Table, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8. de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nying of a fundamental point of faith, the Reſurrection of the dead, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. And to give an inſtance more eſpecially perti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent to the queſtion in hand, many of them came to the Lords Table drunken, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.21. and ſo did eate and drink dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation: Notwithſtanding this deluge of corruption the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament was adminiſtred, and the Apoſtle gave no directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to the contrary, though he treated purpoſely and at large touching abuſes about the Lords Supper, and gave them di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections for reformation of them, delivering whatſoever he received of the Lord touching this Argument. It is plaine therefore that forbearing the Lords Supper in ſuch a caſe is no Apoſtolical practice. If this Tenent of our Antagoniſts were true, the eaſieſt and more proper remedy that the Apoſtle could have adviſed them to, was to lay aſide the Lords Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per untill either the Church guides became more watchfull, or the Church Members more reformed in lives and Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſations. But now the Apoſtle falls upon other Remedies of this abuſe.</p>
            <p>Firſt, He cals upon the Church guides to caſt out the ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalous, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. and then,</p>
            <p>Secondly, He exhorts private members to examine themſelves, <hi>and ſo eate of this Bread and drink of this Cup.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>From the firſt remedy, we may, ſupplying ſome Propoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons conclude; That in Un-Presbyterated Churches Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters ſhould uſe their utmoſt endeavours for a Reformation for thee ſetting up of Presbytery in their Churches that may exclude ſcandalous perſons from the Lords Supper. But a to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall forbearance of the Lords Supper, and an endeavour of reformation are things widely different. That this Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment thus drawn <hi>a comparatis</hi> may appeare in its full ſtrength; I ſhall deſire you to conſider what our Divines argue hence againſt ſeparation in caſe of ſufferance of ſcandalous perſons in Church Communion, and you will find that <hi>mutatis mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tandis,</hi> it will ſerve our turne againſt this Non-adminiſtration or totall forbearance of adminiſtration, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="46" facs="tcp:115045:28"/>
            <p>Before I meddle with Objections, I ſhall firſt premiſe ſome Conceſſions which may ſave the labour of alleadging many Arguments, in which there is that Fallacy which is termed <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Ignoratio Elenchi,</hi> a proofe of that which no way oppoſeth what I hold.</p>
            <p>Firſt then, I grant that Perſons groſly ignorant and notori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly ſcandalous and impenitent ought to be excluded from the Lords Supper, but it muſt be done by them only to whom God hath given this power, and in ſuch order and manner as the Lord hath appointed. That is neceſſary (ſaith Mr <hi>Ball</hi> in his Tryal of the grounds tending to ſeparation, <hi>pag.</hi> 190.) to them that have received Commiſſion from God, which is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfull to them that want authority. In the Common-wealth the execution of juſtice is neceſſary; but private perſons muſt not challenge the Sword of the Magiſtrate. In a Corporation no one muſt take that upon himſelf which belongeth to the Common-Councell. Holy things muſt not be given to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane perſons; but every one at his pleaſure muſt not deny holy things to unholy perſons, but unholy perſons muſt be debarred from holy things in ſuch order as God hath preſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Haec diſpenſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio, vel denega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio Sacramenti noneſt conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>randa ut actio judicialis vel inflictiva paenae ſed ſolum, ut prudens ac fidelis adminiſtratio Sacramenti, &amp; ideo non pendet ex teſtibus, aut probationi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus, ſed ſolum ex câſcientiâ, &amp; cognitione, quae prudenti exiſtimatione ſecundum occurren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes circumſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>tias judicatur ſufficiens, ut ſine, incommodo poſſit, &amp; debeat negari Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentum.</hi> S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>es. in part. 3. Thom. Tom. 3. diſp. 67. Sect. 3. pag. 856.</note> The Schoolmen are extremely out in this particular, for they deny the debarring of notorious offenders from the Lords Supper to be an act of Juriſdiction, and ſo they put it into the hands and power of the Miniſter to deny it unto thoſe whom he judgeth to be groſſe and ſcandalous ſinners.</p>
            <p>In a ſecond place I alſo yeeld that in the permiſſion of groſly ignorant and notoriouſly ſcandalous perſons that are impenitent; there is a great ſin committed by all thoſe who have ſufficient power to keep them back, and by all others that are any waies acceſſary thereunto. But now a man cannot be ſaid to be guilty of that, to hinder which he hath done all that he can (I meane all that he can <hi>de jure,</hi> by right, and law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully.)</p>
            <pb n="47" facs="tcp:115045:28"/>
            <p>Which brings me to my third Conceſſion: A Miniſter is bound to uſe all lawfull probable meanes to keep groſly igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant and notoriouſly ſcandalous impenitent ſinners from the Lords Supper: But he is not, for prevention of their coming, obliged to uſe any unlawful meanes. We muſt not do evill that good may come thereof; commit ſin our ſelves, to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent it in others. Now I have proved a totall forbearance of adminiſtring the Lords Supper to be unlawfull. And thoſe with whom I deale in this Controverſie muſt (unleſſe they will go from their own principles) acknowledge, that for a Miniſter to exclude any ſingly and ſolely by himſelf, as alſo to ſeparate and gather a Church are both unlawfull.</p>
            <p>Having premiſed theſe Conceſſions, I come now unto the Objections, which may be reduced unto one principall Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and the other added as confirmations.</p>
            <p>It is unlawful to give the Lords Supper unto groſly igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant and notoriouſly ſcandalous perſons; but ſuppoſing that our Churches in <hi>England</hi> are generally mixt Congregations; it will be impoſſible (as long as they are deſtitute of Ruling-Elders) for the Miniſter to avoid giving the Lords Supper unto groſly ignorant and notoriouſly ſcandalous perſons; un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe he will either aſſume unto himſelfe ſole power of Juriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction, or elſe allow the whole power to exclude. Now the former would be Tyrannical, Prelaticall, and Pope-like, the later would be a diſclaiming of Presbytery, and a march<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing over unto the Tents of the Independents.</p>
            <p>That it is unlawfull and ſinful for a Miniſter to give the Lords Super unto groſly ignorant and notoriouſly ſcandalous perſons, is endeavoured to be proved.</p>
            <p>Firſt, from the fidelity and prudence required in Miniſters as Stewards, which obligeth them not to diſpenſe the Lords Supper unto ſuch unto whom Chriſt would not have it to be given.</p>
            <p>Secondly, From the general nature of the Lords Supper. It is a holy thing, a Pearle of the Goſpel, and therefore ought not to be given unto dogs and ſwine. It is a ſeale of the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, and the Promiſes. And therefore to adminiſter it unto thoſe who viſibly have as yet no ſhare in them, is a viſible and practicall lye.</p>
            <pb n="48" facs="tcp:115045:29"/>
            <p>Laſtly, From the conſequents of adminiſtring the Lords Supper unto groſly ignorant and notoriouſly ſcandalous per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons. Hereupon will follow a Tranſgreſſion of the Rule of Chriſt; pollution of the Sacrament, a participation of the ſin of unworthy receivers. The Schoolmen here have di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers objections which you may ſee in ſuch of them as Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in <hi>tertiam partem Aquinatis. quaeſt.</hi> 80. <hi>Art.</hi> 6.</p>
            <p>The firſt anſwer is by retortion. All theſe Arguments may be retorted upon our diſſenting brethren. For they conclude alſo againſt adminiſtration of the Lords Supper in a Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terated Church, in caſe there be either neglect or Mal-admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtration of Diſcipline: For then conſidering the Conſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of our Churches generally here in <hi>England</hi> how will you avoid giving the Lords Supper unto thoſe groſly ignorant and ſcandalous perſons upon whom the Presbytery hath paſſed no Cenſure if they ſhould preſent themſelves? And that you can by admonition keep them back is altogether unpro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable.</p>
            <p>There be in this caſe but three effectual meanes which the Miniſter can take to prevent the giving of the Sacramentall ſignes unto them. A totall forbearance of the adminiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Lords Supper. The Miniſters excluſion of unworthy perſons ſingly and ſolely by himſelf. Or elſe ſeparation and gathering of a more pure and reformed Church.</p>
            <p>Now of theſe poſſible meanes, I have proved the firſt to be unlawful: And by my Brethrens own Principles the two laſt are unlawfull alſo. If they can think of any other courſe, let them produce it and prove it, and I am confident it will fit our turne as well as theirs.</p>
            <p>Secondly ſome think that the ſuppoſed ſin of giving the Lords Supper unto unworthy perſons is eaſily avoided, if the Miniſter give not the Sacramentall Elements to each Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicant out of his own hand; but the Communicants divide the Elements among themſelves, which was approved of by the old Non-conformiſts; by <hi>Gilleſpy</hi> in his <hi>Aarons Rod bloſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoming. Book</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 8.437.438. By Mr <hi>Bowles de Paſtore Evangelico. lib.</hi> 4. <hi>cap.</hi> 5. By Mr <hi>Burrows</hi> in his <hi>Goſpel-Worſhip,
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:115045:29"/>pag.</hi> 264, 265. and practiſed as <hi>Gerhard</hi> tels us out of <hi>Lavater</hi> by the <hi>Tigurine</hi> Church, <hi>Loc. Theol. Tom.</hi> 5. <hi>de Sacra Caena. cap.</hi> 15. <hi>Cajetan</hi> upon <hi>Matthew</hi> 26. thinks that this courſe is moſt agreeable to the example of Chriſt in the firſt adminiſtration of this Sacrament unto his Apoſtles; as alſo <hi>Salmeron, Janſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius, Caſſander</hi> in <hi>Liturgicis. Suarez</hi> in <hi>part.</hi> 3. <hi>Thom. diſp.</hi> 72. <hi>Sect.</hi> 1. with whom <hi>Maldonate</hi> upon <hi>Matthew</hi> accords. As concerning the Cup <hi>Johannes Buxtorfius junior in Exercitatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne ſacrâ in hiſtoriam inſtitutionis coenae dominicae. Baſil. editâ.</hi> 1642. thinks that Chriſt herein followed the cuſtome of the Jews in the Paſſeover; where the <hi>Pater-familias</hi> bleſſed the bread and brake it; but they who eate the Paſſeover with him, took their portion with their own hands out of the diſh or Platter. Indeed Chriſt gave both the Bread and the Cup to the Diſciples. But we muſt diſtinguiſh between giving of a thing unto many in <hi>genere</hi> and <hi>conjunctim,</hi> in generall and jointly; and the giving of it <hi>viritim &amp; ſigillatim,</hi> ſeverally and to each man.</p>
            <p>It doth not appeare that our Saviour gave the Sacramen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall Elements to his Apoſtles <hi>ſigillatim &amp; viritim;</hi> to each of them out of his own hand, but that he gave them unto them only <hi>conjunctim,</hi> and in <hi>genere,</hi> jointly, and in generall; is at leaſt made very probable by theſe following Arguments.</p>
            <p>Firſt, There is not in either the Evangeliſts, or the 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. any the leaſt mention of our Saviours diſtributing the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentall Elements particularly, and ſeverally out of his own hand to each Communicant: Nay, the contrary rather is probable, becauſe he ſpeaks unto theſe, whom he gave the Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per unto, only jointly and in general. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <p>A ſecond reaſon is given by <hi>Cajetan</hi> on <hi>Matthew</hi> 26. The Diſciples received the Bread and Cup into their hands, not from the hand of Chriſt, but from the Table. For Chriſt is found ſitting at one Table with his Diſciples, unto whom he ſtill ſitting diſtributed the bleſſed Sacrament as unto his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municants: But now they being ſo many ſate, in all likeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood, at ſo great a diſtance as that the hand of Chriſt could not convey it into the hands of each Communicant; And therefore it is probable that Chriſt gave the diſh or platter un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:115045:30"/>him that ſate next unto him, from whom it was ſucceſſive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly reach'd about unto the other Communicants.</p>
            <p>A third Argument is concerning the Cup: whence we may argue unto the Bread by way of Analogy: and it is taken out of <hi>Luk.</hi> 22.17. <hi>And he took the Cup and gave thanks, and ſaid, take this and divide it among your ſelves.</hi> Whereas ſome underſtand the Cup to be the Paſchall Cup; others to be the Cup in the ordinary Supper. To me (ſaith <hi>Gilleſpy</hi> in the place above quoted) it is plaine that it was the Euchariſtical Cup; becauſe that which <hi>Luke</hi> ſaith of that Cup, that Chriſt took it and gave thanks, and gave it to the Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, that they might all drink of it, and told them he would not drink with them any more of the fruit of the Vine till the Kingdom of God ſhall come. All this is the very ſame which <hi>Matthew</hi> and <hi>Mark</hi> record of the Euchariſticall Cup.</p>
            <p>But now it is objected, That this is related before the taking and breaking of the Bread, and therefore it is not likely to be the Euchariſtical Cup which was given after the Bread.</p>
            <p>Unto this <hi>Gilleſpy</hi> replyeth, that it is but by an Anticipati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on or Pre-occupation occaſioned by that which had proceeded, <hi>Verſ</hi> 16. So to joine the Proteſtation of not drinking again, with that of not eating againe the Paſſeover with his Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples. Wherefore <hi>Beza, Salmeron, Maldonate,</hi> and others following <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> and <hi>Euthymeus,</hi> do reſolve, that it is an Anticipation, even as <hi>Paul</hi> mentioneth the Cup before the Bread. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.16. Thus <hi>Gilleſpy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Mr <hi>Burrows</hi> in the but now quoted place gives alſo three reaſons why it is better to give it generally then particularly into every ones hand.</p>
            <p>Firſt, Becauſe that the giving of it once for all doth ſignifie more fully the fellowſhip and Communion that they have to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether. As at a Table, it were a ſtrange thing that every bit of meat muſt be given to every one particularly, no, but the diſhes muſt be ſet before them and they muſt take it them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves. Indeed if they be children you cut every peece of meat and give it into their hands or mouths; but that is futable to a fellowſhip at Table, and Communion to have the meat ſet before them being bleſſed, and then for all to partake of it.</p>
            <pb n="51" facs="tcp:115045:30"/>
            <p>And ſecondly, Beſides this giving it into every ones hand, came to us from a Popiſh and Superſtitious conceit of the Papiſts to bring more reverence to the Sacrament. Now there is a great deale of danger to bring in mens devices to cauſe more reverence.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, one would wonder that Miniſters ſhould give it in particular, and not in generall to the Church; for by this meanes Miniſters might abundantly eaſe themſelves of a great deale of charge and guilt.</p>
            <p>Now if this way of diſtributing the Sacramental Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments in general be juſtifiable; then as Mr <hi>Bowles</hi> ſaith in the place above cited, <hi>Si quis ſe obtrudet, quem ut excluderet, fecit quod in ſe Paſtor non tamille dare, quam hic arripere di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cendus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But in a third place, Take giving of Sacramentall Elements in what ſenſe you pleaſe, we muſt diſtinguiſh of dogs and ſwine, groſly ignorant and ſcandalous impenitent ſinners. They are either ſuch indeed, and really, or elſe juridically by Church Cenſure. It is unlawfull to give the Sacramental Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to the latter ſort, but not alwaies unto the firſt. For though (ſaith Mr <hi>Ball, pag.</hi> 193.) in courſe of life they may be dogs, yet in publike eſteeme they are not to be reputed dogs, nor uſed as dogs till the Church have ſo pronounced of them. And for this <hi>Aquinas part.</hi> 3. <hi>Quaeſt.</hi> 80. <hi>Art.</hi> 6, <hi>quotes Auguſtine Tom.</hi> 9. <hi>lib. de medicin. paeniaentiae, cap</hi> 3. <hi>Nos à Communione quenquam prohibere non poſſumus, niſi ſponte con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſum, aut in aliquo Judicio Eccleſiaſtico vel ſeculari nomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum atque convictum.</hi> Now if only ſuch dogs and ſwine are to be denyed the Lords Supper who are ſuch juridically, then the alleadged arguments will no way oppoſe my opinion; For in a Church without Ruling-Elders there cannot regularly be any ſuch dogs and ſwine.</p>
            <p>That it is only unlawfull for Miniſters to give the Lords Supper unto ſuch dogs and ſwine as are ſo Juridically,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ad commune bonum, &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venientem Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiae vel cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſque reipubli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cae gubernatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem pertinet; ut communia bona, quae pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice diſpenſanda ac diſtribuenda ſunt, juxta me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rita &amp; dignita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem ſingularum perſonarum à publico Miniſtro ad hoc munus à Republica vel principe reipub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licae destinato, diſpenſentur, non juxta privatam ſcientiam ipſius miniſtri, ſed per publicam &amp; notoriem: hujuſmodi autem eſt diſpenſatio Sacramenti hujus, ut per ſe conſtat, ergo quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do publice ſit, non est regulanda per ſcientiam privatam, ſed publicam. Maj<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r propoſitio videtur eſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> morale quoddam principium, ſere ex ipſis terminis notum. Niſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> haec regula in praedicta publica diſpenſatione ſervetur, talis diſpenſandi modus mor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> liter loquendo, erit ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitus multis ſcandalis, perturbationibus, &amp; injuriis: ut miniſtri poſſent facile publice in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>famare, quos vellent, &amp; peccatum, vel indignitatem fingere, ubi non eſſet. Et è contrariò poſſent fideles ſaepe formidare, &amp; timere, ne à miniſtr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s hujus Sacramenti infamarentur. Et hac ratione quamvis peccatur abſolute non habet jus ad petendum hoc Sacramentum, tamen quilibet fidelis haber jus, ut ſi publice p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>at, non repell<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tur, niſi debito mod<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, id eſt ex pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lica manifeſtatione, &amp; ſcientia ſui peccati: propter quod dixit recte divus Thomas, per pec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catum mortale amitti jus petendi hoc Sacramentum, opportere tamen, ut in facie Eccleſiae amit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatur, ſcilicet ut in eadem facie Eccleſiae, id est publice denegari poſſit. Tandem explicatur, &amp; confirmatur hoc, illo communi exemplo de judice, qui tenetur judicare ſecundum allega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta &amp; probata, etiam contra privatam ſcientiam, ſolum obſimile principium, quiae ad commune bonum neceſſarium est, ut illa publica actio reguletur publicâ ſcientiâ, &amp; non privata, quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niam ſi aliter fieret, eſſet res expoſita infinitis injuriis, &amp; ſcandalis.</hi> This place of <hi>Suaraz</hi> is very well rendred by <hi>Ball,</hi> pag. 188, 189. See alſo 190, 191.</note> will I ſuppoſe, be acknowledged by all, both Presbyterians and Inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendents; for otherwiſe they will leave it to the Miniſters diſcretion to exclude whom he thinks in his conſcience unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy: And what is this but to allow him the exerciſe of ſole
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:115045:31"/>power of juriſdiction, contrary to the Rule of Chriſt, <hi>Mat.</hi> 18.17. and the pattern of the Primitive Apoſtolical Church, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.6.</p>
            <p>For a farther proofe of this I ſhall cite an excellent Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment out of <hi>Suarez</hi> in <hi>part.</hi> 3 <hi>Thom. diſp.</hi> 67. <hi>Sect.</hi> 4. which he bringeth to prove that the Euchariſt is not to be denyed unto a ſecret and hidden ſinner; for it may very well be extended unto all ſcandalous ſinners that are not ſuch juridi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally.</p>
            <p>It is requiſite for the common good, and convenient order both of Church and Common-wealth, that all common fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours which are publikly to be diſpoſed and diſtributed ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the dignity of private perſons, ſhould be diſpenſed by publike Miniſters deſigned thereunto, not according to the private knowledge of this or that man; neither of that Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter, but according to a publike and notorious cogniſance; And whoſoever doth by his offence againſt God loſe his right and intereſt to the holy things of God, he muſt loſe it in the face of the Church, before it can be denied him in the face of the congregation; And he is to be judged (as in all other ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes) not by any mans, nor by any Miniſters private know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, but according to proofes and allegations. For the
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:115045:31"/>Common good neceſſarily requireth that ſuch publike actions of this nature ſhould be regulated by a kind of publike and not private knowledge, which once admitted into Judicature, would ſoone fill up the Church and State with a world of ſcandals, injuries, and inconveniences. For hereby a wicked or a peeviſh and pettiſh Miniſter may without controul pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likely diſgrace and repell from the Lords Supper whom he pleaſe. He may falſely object unworthineſſe unto the moſt worthy, ſuch as are beſt qualified and fitted of all the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation for receiving the Lords Supper. Men would be loath (ſaith Mr <hi>Ball, pag.</hi> 191.) to put their Lands, nay, their Goods and Cattels, and ſhall we think the Lord hath put their intereſt in the body and bloud of Chriſt to a private di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcretion?</p>
            <p>To exclude from the Lords Supper is a kind of Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call puniſhment, and therefore preſuppoſeth an Eccleſiaſtical Cenſure; though men have deſerved ſuch a puniſhment, yet is it not to be inflicted on them untill they be legally cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured.</p>
            <p>But that a Miniſter may in ſome caſes give the Lords Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per unto ſuch perſons as he knoweth to be unworthy and ſcandalous, will appeare from the Conceſſions of our diſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting brethren.</p>
            <p>For firſt, If the Church be Presbyterated there may be a neglect, or Mal-adminiſtration of Diſcipline, and then do the Miniſter what he can, there may be by the major part of the Elderſhip admitted unto the Lords Supper ſuch perſons as the Miniſter knoweth to be dogs and ſwine, ſcandalous, and unworthy; and they not being ſo juridically, the Miniſter cannot debar them, unleſſe he will either uſurp ſole power of Juriſdiction, or elſe run upon the rock of ſeparation.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Suppoſe that the exerciſe of Diſcipline be ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſo rigid and ſtrict; yet how will he keep from the Lords Supper ſecret and hidden ſinners known only unto him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe.</p>
            <p>Suppoſe a Miniſter by himſelf only, without any other witneſſe, ſee a lurking Hypocrite of his Congregation com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit a lewd and great ſcandall; the Miniſter after ſeveral ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monitions
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:115045:32"/>(the party remaining obſtinate and impenitent) complaineth of him to the Church, but he denies the fact: Whereupon the Church can do nothing in the buſineſſe; For her Cenſures be to paſſe either upon the parties confeſſion, or the teſtimony of two or three witneſſes. In this caſe I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand whether or no a Miniſter may lawfully keep back this Hyppocrite from the Lords Supper? If you ſay that he may lawfully in ſuch a caſe keep him back, why then you will aſcribe unto the Miniſter ſuch a vaſt and boundleſſe power, as any modeſt man will be loath to challenge, upon exerciſe of which, more miſchiefes will enſue then can poſſible be fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeen. You will make the Miniſters private judgement to be final, from which there is no appeale to any Court but the Court of heaven; for no earthly Court can lawfully proceed but <hi>Secundum allegata &amp; probata.</hi> Such crimes as we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not prove are reſerved for the notice and vengeance of God.</p>
            <p>But if now on the other ſide you affirme that it is not law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full for the Miniſter to keep back this Hyppocrite; it will fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low then, that there may be ſome dogs and ſwine, unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy receivers, whom the Miniſters knows to be ſuch, unto whom it may yet be lawfull for him to give the Lords Supper, <hi>viz.</hi> ſuch as he cannot convict for want of witneſſes. And I conceive that it is altogether as lawfull for him to give it unto ſuch as he cannot convict for want of Judges.</p>
            <p>However, hereupon it is evident that this Propoſition, That it is unlawfull and ſinful for a Miniſter to give the Lords Supper unto dogs and ſwine, unworthy and ſcandalous per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, is not, abſolutely and univerſally true. Now if they will be pleaſed to limit the Propoſition, and to ſhew in what caſe it holds, and in what not; they may perchance ſay ſomething that may cut the throat of all their Arguments.</p>
            <p>As for the Objections of the Schoolemen they will little ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage our diſſenting brethren.</p>
            <p>For firſt, They leave it unto the diſcretion of the Miniſter to deny the Euchariſt unto ſuch, as he in his conſcience thinks to be open and publike ſcandalous ſinners; and ſuch a power our brethren will not allow unto any Miniſter ſingly by him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf.</p>
            <pb n="55" facs="tcp:115045:32"/>
            <p>Then ſecondly, they ſpeak very doubtfully, and uncertainly, and leave a Miniſter in perplexity; for they ſay, it is lawfull unto Miniſters to give the Sacrament to the unworthy, when they cannot refuſe them without ſcandall. Now (ſaith M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Aarons</hi> Rod bloſſoming. <hi>lib.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 10.</note> 
               <hi>Gill<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſpy</hi>) If the lawfulneſſe or unlawfulneſſe of the thing muſt be determined by the ſcandall they go upon a very ſlippery ground. As ſlippery and uncertain is another reſtriction which they joyne unto the former, <hi>viz.</hi> That it is lawful for a Miniſter to give the Sacrament to the unworthy when they cannot keep them back, without great inconveniency or inex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pediency. <hi>Suarez in 3<hi rend="sup">am</hi>. part. Thom. diſp.</hi> 67. <hi>ſect.</hi> 1. Saith, that the precept of not giving this Sacrament unto the unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy, is not ſimply negative, but is to be reduced unto an affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mative precept, of prudently, and faithfully diſpenſing this Sacrament. <hi>Quod praeceptum quidem formaliter ſumptum (ut ſic dicam) ſemper ſervandum eſt, quotieſcunque hoc Sacramen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum diſpenſatur: &amp; hinc fit ut ſi commodè poſſit, debeat indigno denegari, non tamen quod ſemper denegari debeat cum cocunque in commodo &amp; ſine ulla exceptione.</hi> Theſe laſt words of <hi>Sua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rez</hi> together with thoſe of <hi>Gilleſpy,</hi> will ſerve to anſwer all the Arguments of the Schoolmen, ſo farre as they are urged a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt us. For in an Un-Presbyterated Church, the Lords Supper cannot be denyed unto unworthy perſons without ſcandall, great inconveniences; nay, I beleeve, ſinne.</p>
            <p>And this for a general anſwer unto all the Arguments, I ſhall next examine each argument a part.</p>
            <p>The firſt Argument is taken from that fidelity and prudence required in Miniſters as ſtewards of the myſteries of God, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.1, 2. and it is urged by <hi>Suarez in 3<hi rend="sup">am</hi>. partem Thom. diſp.</hi> 18. <hi>ſect.</hi> 2. <hi>diſp.</hi> 67. <hi>ſect.</hi> 1. As alſo by <hi>Becanus, ſumm. Theolog. parte 3<hi rend="sup">ia</hi>. tract.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 5. <hi>Quaeſt.</hi> 8.
<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Praeceptum naturale eſt ut diſpenſator qui bona Domini ſui diſpenſat, ſit fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delis &amp; prudens in diſpenſando ergo praeceptum naturale eſt ut non diſpenſet homini indigno contra volunta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem &amp; inſiitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionem ſui do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mini quia hoc eſſet contra fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delitatem &amp; prudentiam quam indiſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſando debet ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vare cum ergo non velit Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menta ſua diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſari indig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis non poteſt Miniſter ſi fide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis eſſe vult, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra hanc volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatem facere.</hi>
               </note> Stewards (ſay they) ought to be faithful and prudent in diſtribution of the goods of their Lord and Maſter; and therefore they ſhould not diſpenſe them againſt his will and appointment. Now for Miniſters to give the Lords Supper unto known unworthy re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceivers, is to diſtribute it againſt the will and appoyntment of their Lord and Maſter Chriſt Jeſus. And therefore a violati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of that prudence and fidelity which is required at their hands.</p>
            <pb n="56" facs="tcp:115045:33"/>
            <p>For anſwer. Firſt, I ſhall deſire you to apply unto this Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument the generall Anſwers, and then the Argument may be retorted upon our <hi>Antagoniſts.</hi> Prudence and fidelity obligeth ſtewards, all ſuch as have committed unto them the diſpenſation of the goods, food, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> of their Maſter unto the houſhold; not to go beyond their commiſſion, not to uſurp the exerciſe of a power, which their Maſter hath for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden them by themſelves, only to meddle with as being gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven in commiſſion joyntly with them unto their fellow Stew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ards. Now they ſhould go beyond their commiſſion, and aſſume a power for which they can ſhew no warrant from their Lord and Maſter, if they ſhould ſingly and ſolely by themſelves debarre any from the Lords Supper.</p>
            <p>Secondly, There would be little colour in the Argument, if it were not for the ambiguity that is in the terme <hi>Gods will.</hi> Here if the Objection, conclude any thing againſt us: The <hi>Will of God</hi> muſt be taken Metonimycally for that which they call <hi>Voluntas ſigni,</hi> in particular the Command of God; and then the Argument is nothing but a pitifull and miſerable beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging of the Queſtion. For that there is a command unto the Miniſter, not to give the Lords Supper unto unworthy per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, who are not ſuch juridically, is not ſo much as attempted to be proved.</p>
            <p>A ſecond Objection is taken from the generall nature of the Lords Supper. It is a holy thing, a Pearle of the Goſpel, a Seal of the Covenant of grace.</p>
            <p>Firſt, It is a holy thing, a Pearle of the Goſpel, and our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viours command is, <hi>Matth.</hi> 7.6. <hi>Give not that which is holy unto dogges, neither caſt ye your Pearle before ſwine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sufficient ſatisfaction is given unto this place by the general Anſwers, yet becauſe it is much ſtood upon, I ſhall ſay ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing unto it apart.</p>
            <p>Firſt, this place, as appears both by the Coherence, as alſo by the reaſon annexed is principally intended concerning ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monitions and reproofe. For if you look upon the words foregoing, you ſhall finde a direction for the reprover, that he be not ſpotted with greater faults, then thoſe which he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proveth
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:115045:33"/>in others. Then in this Verſe there is directions con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the perſons to be reproved, that they be not dogges and ſwine. But the reaſon annexed leſt they turne again, and rent you, makes the matter quite out of Queſtion: For the giving of the Lords Supper unto the prophaneſt wretches al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt that are, is not likely to occaſion any ſuch car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage.</p>
            <p>But yet I will not deny that the place may be extended and applyed unto the giving of the Lords Supper unto unworthy receivers; but then it muſt bee <hi>cum grano ſalis.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Giving of the Lords Supper may be taken either for the authoritative and juridicall admiſſion unto, or elſe for the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſteriall diſtribution of the Lords Supper.</p>
            <p>Firſt then, if you take it for the juridicall and authoritative admiſſion unto the Lords Supper, then indeed it is true that the Lords Supper ought not to be given unto ſwine or dogges: they ought not authoritatively or juridically to be admitted thereunto; but then we ſay that the Commandment is not given unto the Miniſter ſolely, but unto the whole Elderſhip, and thus M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Bowles</hi> anſwereth the place. <hi>Praeceptum, de non dando quod ſanctum canibus, eos duntaxat obligat, quibus Deus a ſacris arcendi canes poteſtatem demandavit; &amp; haec non uni alicui, ſed pluribus à Chriſto tradita.</hi> With reference unto this is it that M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Ball</hi> tels us. <hi>pag.</hi> 204.205. that the Miniſter if he have done the office of a private Chriſtian, and a pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique Miniſter, and afterward he reach the Sacrament unto an unworthy Communicant, he doth not ſo much give it him, as ſuffer his Communion, becauſe he hath not power or authority to put him back: He reacheth him the ſignes, as that which he cannot with-hold, becauſe he is held in by the moſt prevail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing power, without which he cannot be debarred. In this caſe the Miniſter is neither actor nor conſenter in his admiſſion, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he doth it not in his own name, but according to the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der eſtabliſhed by God, who will not have any member of the Congregation publiquely denyed his intereſt and right to the holy things of God, by the knowledge, will and pleaſure of one ſingular Miniſter. If a Miniſter know a man to be unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy, he may yet receive him, becauſe he cannot yet manifeſt
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:115045:34"/>it to the Church: And for the ſame reaſon, if his unworthy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe be notorious, if it be not ſo judged by them that have authority, he muſt adminiſter the Sacramentall ſignes unto him, not as unto one worthy, or unworthy, but as unto one yet undivided from them.</p>
            <p>If you take giving of the Lords Supper for the Miniſterial diſtribution of the Elements; why then again I grant the Lords Supper is not to be given unto dogs and ſwine, provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded that they be ſuch juridically by Church cenſure, and ſo this precept binds not abſolutely, but conditionally upon a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition that dependeth upon the Elderſhip, and not upon the Miniſter ſolely.</p>
            <p>And thus again the reverend <hi>Bowles</hi> anſwereth the place:
<note place="margin">Qui omnium peſſim<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, uſque dum Eccleſia eos ſuâ ſenten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiâ decretoriâ pro cambus &amp; porcis habendos declaraverit, non mihi cum illis ut canibus &amp; porcis agendum. Latronem, qui mortem commeruit, nullus jure de vita tollat, uſque dum judex &amp; reum declaraverit, &amp; ſententiam tulerit.</note> I am not to deal with the worſt of men, as dogs and ſwine, until the Church hath ſentenced them to be ſuch. Suppoſe a felon hath deſerved death, yet the Sheriffe himſelf cannot lawfully execute him untill he be tryed, and the judge hath condemned him.</p>
            <p>If any ſhould argue from this place for a Miniſters not gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving of the Lords Supper unto ſuch dogs and ſwine as are not ſo by Church cenſure; I hope they deſire to be underſtood not abſolutely, but limitedly, ſo farre forth as it lyeth in a Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter. And this I readily yeeld unto, as no way impugning my opinion. I do confeſſe that a Miniſter is to keep dogges and ſwine from the Sacrament, ſo farre as in him lyeth (that is, he is to do all that God hath required at his hands for pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention thereof:) But I am very confident that this grant of mine will no wayes prejudice my cauſe, or advantage that of my oppoſites; becauſe God for prevention of wicked mens Sacramentall approaches nowhere requireth a Miniſter to u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurp a power which is none of his, a ſole power of juriſdiction, <hi>in foro Eccleſiaſtico externo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But the Schoolmen endeavour to prove not only from the but now mentioned place of Scripture, but alſo from reaſon:
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:115045:34"/>That it is a ſinne to give the Lords Supper unto ſuch as a man knowes to be unworthy receivers.</p>
            <p>Great is the dignity and holineſſe of this bleſſed Sacrament,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Obligatio exhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bendi reveren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiam huic Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cramento, &amp; digne illud tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctandi, natura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis eſt, ex intrin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecâ ipſius Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cramenti digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate orta; ad hanc vero per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinet obligatio non dandi Sacramentum hoc indignis: Sicut non projicere illud in locum immundum, &amp; ſimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lia.</hi> Suarez in tertiam part. Thom. diſp. 67. ſect. 1. <hi>Is dicitur ſacrilegium committere qui violat rem Sacram per aliquam irreverentiam.</hi> D. Thom. 2.2. Q. 99. a. 2.3. <hi>Atqui Miniſter conferens Sacramentum homini indigno, violat rem Sacram per quandam irreveren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiam; ergo ſacrilegium committit.</hi> Becanus ſu mma Theol. par. 3. tract. 2. cap. 5. Sect. 8.</note> and therefore it ſhould be handled in a meet, decent, reverent, and devout manner. Now it were a very undecent and unre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verent part to take the Elements aſſoone as conſecrated and wittingly to throw them into a noyſome ſinke; but it is a point of greater irreverence, nay, it is a kind of Sacriledge, to take them and give them unto known unworthy receivers: for no ſink is ſo foule, dirty and ſtinking as a ſinful, earthy and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleanſed ſoul.</p>
            <p>For anſwer, I deny that there is any ſacriledge or irreve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence in a Miniſters giving the Sacrament unto unworthy per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, who are not ſuch juridically; provided ſtill that he uſe all lawfull likely means to keep them off. And the Schoolmen themſelves confeſſe as much concerning hidden and ſecret ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners; as alſo when a Miniſter cannot avoid the giving of it un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them without ſcandall or ſome other great inconvenience. Indeed the dignity and holineſſe of the Sacrament is ſacrilegi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly violated by the irreverence of unworthy receivers; But God hath not left his Church infallible means to keep his Name and Ordinances from irreverence: And the Miniſter is not guilty of this irreverence in unworthy receiving, though he give them the Sacramental Elements, if he do what lyeth in him to keep them off, and when he cannot hinder them he give them the Elements with regret, with a mourning and bleeding heart; I ſhall conclude my anſwer unto this Obje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection with that of <hi>Suarez praedictâ diſputatione Section.</hi> 4. <hi>Ipſemet Chriſtus vult ut aliqua ejus injuria potius permittatur, quàm indebito modo ac ordine caveatur.</hi> It is Chriſts will ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther that there ſhould be a permiſſion of wrongs and injuries
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:115045:35"/>unto his Name, Ordinances and Sacraments, then that they ſhould be prevented by unlawfull means, in an undue either order or manner.</p>
            <p>A ſecond generall Attribution of the Lords Supper, from whence it is endeavoured to conclude to the ſinfulneſſe of gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving it in any caſe, unto ſuch as are known by the Miniſter to be unworthy receivers, is, its being a ſeal of the Covenant of Grace, the righteouſneſſe of Faith. For hence think ſome, it followeth that adminiſtration of the Lords Supper unto known ſcandalous and wicked perſons, is a practicall and viſible lye, a confirmation of an untruth, becauſe it ſeals the Covenant and Promiſes to thoſe who have viſibly no ſhare in them.</p>
            <p>For anſwer, The Lords Supper may be ſaid to be a ſeal of the Covenant, or Promiſe of Grace, either abſolutely, or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditionally. The truth of the Covenant and Promiſes in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, our obligation to gratitude and obedience, are ſealed abſolutely by the Lords Supper; but intereſt in the Covenant and Promiſes of Grace, the Lords Supper ſealeth unto thoſe that partake thereof, but conditionally, ſo they beleeve: Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to wicked men the Promiſes are as propounded, ſo ſealed but conditionally. <hi>Sacramenta</hi> (ſaith <hi>Ameſius</hi>) <hi>non ſunt Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monia completa &amp; abſoluta niſicredentibus.</hi> They are (ſaith <hi>Rutherford</hi>) ſeals unto the wicked, not in <hi>actu ſecundo,</hi> but on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in <hi>actu primo.</hi> See M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Marſhall</hi> in his defence of Infant Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme againſt <hi>Tombs pag.</hi> 117.118.</p>
            <p>The laſt ſort of Objections proving that it is a ſin to give the Lords Supper unto known ſcandalous ſinners, is drawn from the conſequents that will follow upon diſtribution of the Sacramentall Elements unto them.</p>
            <p>Firſt, tranſgreſſion of the Rule of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Secondly, pollution of the Sacrament.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, a participation of the ſinne of unworthy re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceivers.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, a Communion with wicked men in worſhip, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt then upon a Miniſters giving the Sacramental ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments unto them, there will follow a tranſgreſſion of the
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:115045:35"/>Rule of Chriſt, which by my owne confeſſion excludeth ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalous ſinners, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>For anſwer; Upon a Miniſters giving the Sacramental ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments unto known ſcandalous ſinners, that are not ſuch by Church cenſure (for of ſuch only we ſpeak) there will follow a tranſgreſſion of the Rule of Chriſt: but by whom? by the known ſcandalous ſin in unworthy receiving, by the Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guides in caſe the Church be Presbyterated, if they either miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>govern or neglect the exerciſe of diſcipline; and by the Church, if ſhe (in caſe ſhe be unſetled and un-reformed) do not endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour the choice of Church-officers. But there can be no rule broken by the Miniſter herein, who hath done his duty for the keeping of them off; for he had never any Rule or Command given unto him, for denyal of the Lords Supper unto unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy Perſons, that are not ſuch Juridically; or for delay and ſuſpenſion of the Lords Supper, in caſe an Elderſhip be not ſet up in a Congregation. <hi>In modo recipiendi Sacramenti</hi> (ſaith <hi>Suarez</hi>) <hi>duo poſſunt conſiderari: unum eſt ex parte ipſius Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cramenti; ſcilicet quod vere, integrè &amp; cum debitis circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiis fiat; Aliud eſt ex parte effectus Sacramenti, &amp; conſequen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ex parte diſpoſitionis ſuſcipientis, quae ad effectum eſt neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria. In tertiam part. Thom. diſp.</hi> 17. <hi>ſect.</hi> 2.</p>
            <p>Now if a Miniſter give the Sacrament unto known unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy Perſons, that are not ſuch Juridically, there is not hereby any tranſgreſſion of the rule of Chriſt, in regard of the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment it ſelfe, which notwithſtanding this, may fully and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirely be adminiſtred according to the command of Chriſt. But there will follow a tranſgreſſion of the Rule of Chriſt hereby, in reſpect of the effect of the Sacrament, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently the diſpoſitions and qualifications required in recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers to make the Sacrament effectual: but this is not a fault chargeable upon the Miniſter if he do his beſt to prevent it. More plainly; Corruption and defects, or breaches of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand and rule of Chriſt in the adminiſtration of the Lords Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, are of two ſorts; Material, or Perſonal. Firſt material, when the Worſhip it ſelf is corrupted, as in the Popiſh maſte, where there is but one element. Secondly Perſonal, when the Worſhip it ſelf is in every reſpect pure, but the Perſons
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:115045:36"/>communicating, wanting in requiſite qualifications; the former are chargeable upon the Miniſter adminiſtring the Lords Supper; not the latter, ſo he prevent them as farre as in him lyeth.</p>
            <p>Secondly, it is objected that upon a Miniſters giving of the Lords Supper unto known wicked Perſons, there will neceſſarily follow a pollution and a prophanation of that ſacred ordinance; the giving of it therefore unto them is a ſin.</p>
            <p>For anſwer; The Lords Supper (and ſo we may ſay the like of other Ordinances) may be ſaid to be polluted either intrinſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally, or extrinſecally. Intrinſecal pollutions are in ordinances themſelves when they are ſo corrupted, that whoſoever par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takes of them, in the very partaking, cannot but break Gods order. And ſo the Lords Supper is polluted in the Popiſh Maſſe, where the bread is adored, where they have but one Element, directly againſt Chriſt his inſtitution. Extrinſecal pollutions or prophanations of the Lords Supper, (and we may ſay the like of other ordinances) are, when for want of due qualifications, they become ſin unto the unworthy receiver, even as the Prayers of the wicked are an abomination to him.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>The Toleration of Drunkards and Swearers in the Lords Church, and at his Table, infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cteth, and is apt to leaven all with their evill converſation, but doth not leaven the worſhip unto the fellow-worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers; Nor is the ſin of private Perſons, yea, nor of the Miniſters, who have no power to helpe them.</hi> Rutherford in his due right of Presbyt.</note> But now theſe pollutions of the Lords Supper by un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy receivers, do not defile the Lords Supper in it ſelf, nor to others who receive it worthily. <hi>He that eateth and drink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth unworthily, eateth and drinketh damnation, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> to himſelf,</hi> not to others.</p>
            <p>This diſtinction thus premiſed; Firſt the conſequence of the Argument in the objection is denyed; becauſe the pollution and prophanation of the Lords Supper, that the objection ſpeaks of, is extrinſecal, not in the Sacrament it ſelf, but only in the unworthy receiver. And again, we ſuppoſe that the Miniſter hath uſed all lawful likely means to prevent it. And therefore it is without his default.</p>
            <p>Secondly, the Argument will hold againſt giving the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:115045:36"/>unto a ſecret and hidden ſinner, that is known only unto the Miniſter (for ſuch a one pollutes and prophanes the Sacrament, as well as the open and known ſinner) and yet thoſe who diſſent from us, will not affirme that the giving of it unto ſuch a one is unlawful.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, it is objected that a Participation of, or Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion with the ſin of others, is a grievous ſin, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.22. Be not Partakers of other mens ſins, keep thy ſelf pure. But to give the Lords Supper to a known wicked Perſon, is to par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take of his ſin of unworthy receiving; and therefore it is ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full.</p>
            <p>For anſwer, firſt when other mens ſins follow accidentally upon the performance of my duty, this is no participation of other mens ſins.</p>
            <p>2<hi rend="sup">ly</hi>. a man can't be ſaid to partake of the ſins of others,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Nullus te net u ut non alterius peccati parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceps ſit facere quod injuſtum: injuſtum autem illud foret, ſi ille ſolus arripi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ret ſibi potesta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem, quam ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cietati Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terorum credi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derit Deus.</hi> Bowls p. 192.</note> when he hath uſed all due and obliged diligence for prevention and hinderance of them; A man is only to do all that he can by his calling, by Warrant and Commiſſion from Chriſt to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent ſin in another. A Miniſter therefore, to prevent unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy receiving in ſcandalous Perſons, is not to paſſe the bounds of his calling, to play the Pope, and uſurp that power which God hath ſeated only in the Elderſhip. Power being wanting, the will ſtands for the deed, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8.12. This is alſo acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged by Mr. <hi>Gilleſpy. lib.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 15. The ſuffering of a mix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of known wicked Perſons among the Godly in the Church, doth ſometime defile us with ſin, ſometime not. It doth not defile us, when we uſe all lawful and poſſible reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies againſt it: and namely when we exerciſe the diſcipline of excommunication and other Church-cenſures, ſaith <hi>Auguſtine. lib. contra Donatiſtas poſt collationem. cap</hi> 4. <hi>Tom.</hi> 7. But it doth defile us, and we incurre ſinne and wrath, when the means of redreſſing ſuch known evils are neglected, <hi>indiſcipli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nata patientia</hi> (it is <hi>Auguſtines</hi> word) ſo to bear with wicked men, as not to execute diſcipline againſt them; that certainly makes us partake of their ſin (I mean in a reformed and well-conſtituted Church, where the thing is feaſable;) but where it cannot be done becauſe of perſecution, or becauſe of the invin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cible oppoſition, either of authority, or of a prevalent pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:115045:37"/>multitude,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Miniſter per ſe loqu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ndo non poteſt dare Sacramentum indgno, ne co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>operetur pecca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to illius. Ratio eſt: quia qui indignè recipit Sacramentum, peccat mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taliter. Ergo qui cooperatur ad talem recep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionem cooperatur ad peccatum. At nemo magis cooperatur ad talem receptionem, quam Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter qui dat Sacramentum.</hi> Becanus. <hi>Nulla poteſt eſſe major cooperatio ad recipiendum quàm ipſumet dare.</hi> Suarez.</note> we have only this comfort left us, <hi>Bleſſed are they that hunger and thirſt after righteouſneſſe;</hi> And, <hi>in magnis voluiſſe ſat est.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But this objection is ſomewhat more ſpeciouſly urged by the ſchoolmen. He partakes of the ſinne of another, who knowingly cooperates thereunto; but a Miniſter that gives the Lords Supper unto ſuch Perſons as he knows to be unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy, cooperates unto their unwo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>thy receiving; for a man can hardly more cooperate unto the receiving of a thing, then by giving it. Thus <hi>Suarez</hi> and <hi>Becanus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For anſwer I may reſerre you unto the ſchoolmen them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves;
<note place="margin">
                  <p>
                     <hi>Qui autem moraliter non potest negare, ſed ſola neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate coactus, dat alteri Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>tamentum, non cooperatur ad indignam ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptionem, ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum Phyſice ad nudam actio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>cipien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis.</hi> Becanus.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>In aliquocaſu accid<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>repotest, ut Miniſter moraliter non poſſit negare Sacramentum homini iniquo petentip<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>opter ſcandalum vel ſimilem cauſam. Et tunc quamvis ille det, non coopera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur iniquae receptioni ut iniqua eſt, ſed ſolum ut receptio Sacramenti est.</hi> Suarez in part. 3. Thom-diſp 18 ſect. 2. But more fully diſp. 67. ſect. 4. <hi>Reſpondetur actionem dandi Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chariſtiam homini indigno non ſemper eſſe intrinſecè malum, ſed tunc ſolum quando ipſe qui dat Sacramentum eſt aliquo modo cauſa indignae ſuſceptionis, vel quando commode vel debito modo exercendo munus ſuum potest vitare, &amp; non facit. Ac denique quando illi conſtat, eum, qui petit, eſſe indignum ea ſcientia &amp; modo quo opus eſt. At vero quando moraliter vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tare non potest actionem dandi, quia prava diſpoſitio petentis non eſt illo modo cognita, quo o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pus eſt, tum act<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> dandi non eſt mala ex parte dantis, &amp; intentio ej<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>s eſt bona, quamvis ex parte recipientis receptio ſit mala, quod null<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> modo imputatur danti, quia nullo modo eſt cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſa, quòd alius indigne ſumat, neque cum actione ejus est per ſe &amp; neceſſariò conjunct a indigna ſuſceptia. Quamobrem i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>i eſt nulla conperatio ad malum, ſed ſola permiſſio quae moraliter vita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri non potest. Nam qui dat Sacramentum ſolum cooperatur, ut hic homo ſumat, non tamen ut in dignè ſumat: Poſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>t enim ſi vellet digne Jumere, quam<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>is autem ſacerdoti conſtet, hi &amp; nunc indigne ſumpturum, tamen quia non poteſtid vitare, ideo neque te<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>etur, neque ulla cenſetur cooperatio ſed permiſſio.</hi>
                  </p>
               </note> what they ſay, I ſhall give you in brief; one may be ſaid to cooperate unto known wicked Perſons their unworthy receiving either <hi>Morally</hi> or <hi>Phyſically;</hi> he only cooperates unto it morally, that is a cauſe of the unworthineſſe of their recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving; and ſo do all they, and only they, who do not uſe all en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyned means to hinder: but now if a Miniſter hath given all due and obliged dilgence, to prevent the unworthy receiving of wicked Perſons, though he gave them the Sacrament, yet he concurreth unto their unworthy receiving only Phyſically, not Morally, that is, he cooperates with their receiving it, not
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:115045:37"/>with the unworthineſſe of their receiving it. He cooperates with it as it is an action; but if you look upon it as a ſinful and depraved action, ſo he doth not cooperate with it, but only permit it much againſt his will, it not being in his power to help it. If any think that this is but a ſchool nicety, a world of ſtances from common experience will condemne them. Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinate officers may cooperate Phyſically to the execution of an unjuſt ſentence, who yet may have no moral concurrence unto the injuſtice thereof. Subjects may cooperate Phyſically not morally, unto an unjuſt warre of the ſupream Magiſtrate. The Head of a Colledge having no negative voice, and being over-voted by the major part of fellows, may <hi>pro formâ</hi> give admiſſion unto an unworthy fellow, and yet not be guilty of any ſin in his admiſſion. For he admits him not in his owne name, but in the name of the major part, who have overborn him, he cooperates then unto his admiſſion Phyſically, not mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally.</p>
            <p>If a Miniſter have done all that lawfully he may for the keeping back of unworthy receivers; and they will not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding crowd in amongſt the worthy: if after this he reach out the Sacramental elements unto them: although he be active in a Phyſical ſenſe, he is only paſſive in a moral ſenſe. It may be a great grief and burthen to his ſpirit, but yet it is not his ſin. Thoſe holy Virgins mentioned in Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal hiſtory, which to eſcape raviſhment laid violent hands on themſelves, are deſervedly blamed. For we are not to commit one ſinne for the avoiding of another. When we have done as much as lawfully we may, for the reſiſting of ſinne, then whatſoever befalleth, may be (as <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſaid of thoſe Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins) our vexation and miſery, but not our ſinne. This an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer may receive ſtrength from this conſideration, that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving of the Lords Supper by wicked and ungodly Perſons is a ſin not <hi>ex objecto &amp; intrinſece,</hi> but only by accident,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Vtcunque agere videtur, qui Sacramentum indigno inter dignosg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> tim ſe admiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centi porrigit, cum tamen fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerit quod ei fas ut arceret paſtor, non re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vera agit ſed patitur. San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctae illae virgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, quae ſibi, nè conſtupra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentur manu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> inj<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>cere violentas, merit ò culpantur: nec enim quis malo obſiſtendo tenetur, ulera quam fas progredi; ubi fecerit quantum jure potest renitendo, quicquid ultra fit (ut de illis Virgimbus olim Auguſtinus) ejus vexatio non peccatum.</hi> Bowls 290.291. <hi>Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menti ceenoe finis quod ad deum, primarius eſt, ut mors domini commemoretur, ejus recorda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio à quam plurimis fiat; quidni vel ex eo gloria accedat deo, cum à frequentiori coetu utcun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que non ut oportebat expurgato, ſacrum hoc epulum celebratur? Si enim vel ex corvis per in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinctum Deum invocantib us, gloria <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>i accreſcit; ſic enim Creator, ut ſons omnium bonorum agnoſcitur; quidni cum confertìm in unum conveniunt homines, de quibus id lugendum, quod non omni modo ad Chriſti opus redemptorium celebrandum idonei? fateor, deo ex eo aucti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>or cederet gloria ſi ab iis, qui vitae puritate ſplendeſcerent, cultus hic exhiberetur; at, vel ex eo, nonnibil deoredundat gloriae, cum ut mundi per Christum redemptor a cunctis agnoſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eur. Ad tam excellentis beneficii memoriam in Eccleſiâ perpetuendam, conveniunt coetus, ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cunque non debite praeparatus, numeroſior.</hi> Bowls 293, 294.</note> 
               <hi>ex prava diſpoſitione ſubjecti;</hi> beſides as Mr. <hi>Bowls</hi> obſerveth, their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving the Lords Supper may ſomeways conduce unto the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mary end thereof, in regard of God: the external ſhewing
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:115045:38"/>and repreſentation of Chriſts death, the publike celebration of the work of our Redemption, and ſo may redound ſomewhat unto the honour and glory of God: for God is in ſome ſort glorified by the outward performance of the duties of wicked men. Now he that cooperates with an action that is good in it ſelf materially or objectively, and only ſinful by accident, may be farre from cooperating with the ſinfulneſſe of that a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction. For he may no ways be a cauſe thereof.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, it is objected that upon giving the Lords Supper unto known ſcandalous ſinners, a religious Communion with them in worſhip will enſue; therefore to give it to them is a ſinne; for what were this but to turn the Communion of Saints into a Communion of ſinners?</p>
            <p>For anſwer; firſt this objection is taken from an Indepen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent forge, and will not be owned by Presbyterians that un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand their own Principles. The old non-Conformiſts wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting againſt the ſeparation, reſolve generally that the Lords Supper may be partaken of in a Church, where ſcandals are tolerated. For we are not (ſay they) to omit a Worſhip for the ſins of our fellow-worſhippers. You may ſay as much in the Vindication of the Presbyterial Government and Miniſters, by the Miniſters and Elders met together in the Provincial Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly at <hi>London, November</hi> 9. 1649. 134.135, 136. Suppoſe (ſay they) there were ſome ſinful mixtures at our Sacraments, yet we conceive this is not a ſufficient ground of a negative ſeparation.</p>
            <p>Secondly, a full and ſufficient anſwer you have to this ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:115045:38"/>in Mr. <hi>Ball, pag.</hi> 200 201. In coming to Gods ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance we have Communion with Chriſt principally, who hath called us thither, is there preſent by his grace and ſpirit to bleſſe his ordinance; and with the faithful, who are there met together at Gods Commandement, in the name and by the authority of Jeſus Chriſt: with the wicked we have no Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion, unleſſe it be external and by accident, becauſe they are not, or cannot be caſt out. Internall and eſſential Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion we have with Chriſt and the faithful only; exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal with the wicked. Our Communion with Chriſt and his faithful People is not free and voluntary, but neceſſary, enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by God, not left to our will or pleaſure. Our Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with the wicked in the ordinances is unwilling on our part, ſuffered not affected, if we know how to hinder it law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully. God requireth attendance on him in his holy ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and to joyne with his Voluntaries aſſembled, where he is preſent in the midſt among them. If we cannot appear before him as duty bindeth, but we muſt have outward Communion with the wicked, which ſhould be expelled, but cannot be kept back by us: In this caſe our Communion with God is free and voluntary, but our Communion with the wicked is ſuffered on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, or held in reſpect of the Will and Commandement of God, who requireth that ſervice at our hands.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="postscript">
            <head>A Poſtſcript.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Chriſtian Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I Thought good to acquaint thee that I have received from one Mr. <hi>Fulwood</hi> a pretended examination of my Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, for the lawfulneſſe of adminiſtring the Lords Supper in an Un-Presbyterated Church: and unto it I have pen'd a very large Reply, for which I am exceedingly blamed by my beſt and moſt knowing friends who unanimouſly tell me, that it is very unfit ſo worthleſſe a Paper ſhould have the honour of a Refutation. If the Author therof think that he hath any wrong by this cenſure, he may right himſelfe by making it as publike as he pleaſe. Moſt of what he ſaith, is either anſwered in this my book, or elſe the abſurdity of it is ſo groſſe and apparent
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:115045:39"/>as that it carrieth a refutation in its own forehead. Indeed there be but two things conſiderable in this pretended examination: An Anſwer, and an Objection.</p>
            <p>The Anſwer is unto my Argument <hi>à Praecepto.</hi> The ſum of it is, That the Command to celebrate the Lords Supper is not immediate, but mediate and conditional; not binding, but upon pre-ſuppoſal of a preparative work of the Presbytery, <hi>&amp;c</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For reply unto this, firſt, all the proofe that he brings for its being a mediate Command, is in 1 <hi>Cor</hi> 14. <hi>ult.</hi> unto which I ſhall preſently give anſwer.</p>
            <p>Secondly, An immediate Command doth not exclude the Command of all Antecedent duties, but only of ſuch upon which the Duty commanded hath an eſſentiall dependency; and anſwerably a mediate Command is that which obligeth not <hi>proximè &amp; immediatè</hi> unto the performance of that which it commandeth, unleſſe there be performance of Antecedent duties upon which it hath an eſſentiall dependency, or an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſtence of any other Antecedents that are before the duty en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joynd, in regard of that order which is of eſſential dependency.</p>
            <p>To give an inſtance of this. The Command to be aſſured of our Juſtification, Vocation, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> is only mediate, and doth not bind immediately, before there be a performance of an Antecedent duty, upon which it hath an eſſentiall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendence, to wit the faith of adherence, before there be an exiſtence of the Objects Vocation, Juſtification, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which are Antecedents unto this aſſurance, in regard of the order of eſſential dependency. It is not therefore the abſence of of every Antecedent that doth ſuſpend, much leſſe evacuate &amp; annul the Obligation of a Command; but only the wants of Antecedents neceſſary by Phyſicall Obligation. A due ſerious and diligent preparation is enjoyned as an Antecedent unto hearing of the word, and unto publike and ſolemn Prayers; and yet I hope Mr <hi>Fullwood</hi> dare not ſay that upon want of preparation there is a ſuſpenſion of the Obligation of theſe Commands of God, to heare and pray: And that in ſuch a caſe not to heare, not to pray, are at the moſt but mediate ſins. It is generally reſolved by all the Caſuiſts that ever I ſaw, that when we come unto a duty and do not find our hearts prepared according unto that we do deſire; that
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:115045:39"/>we are not yet for that time to let go the duty, and forbeare the performance of it. If any one (ſaith Mr. <hi>Burrows</hi> in his <hi>Goſpel-Worſhip</hi>) in anſwer unto the Queſtion) performe a duty in Worſhip in that ſincerity and ſtrength that he is able to do, though he be not prepared as he ought, yet he is better to do it then to neglect it. And he applieth this his anſwer unto receiving of the Sacrament, as well as the Word and Prayer, as may be ſeen by his propoſall of the Queſtion.</p>
            <p>Againe, There are divers things required in the call and Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dination of a Miniſter that are by Gods command to be An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tecedent unto his preaching unto his flock. Some of which are wanting in ſuch Miniſters as were ordained by Biſhops.</p>
            <p>But becauſe they are not Antecedents eſſentially neceſſary unto the preaching of the Word, by the want of them, the Obligation unto the preaching of the word is not ſuſpended, much leſſe annulled. And yet it is not denied but that the want of them is ſinful, for which ſuch Miniſters ought to be humbled. <hi>Scotus lib.</hi> 4, <hi>Diſtinct.</hi> 12 <hi>Queſt.</hi> 3. <hi>num.</hi> 32. thus limits this Propoſition. <hi>Deſtructo priori, destruitur poſterius. Vera eſt</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>de ſimpliciter priori, à quo ſcilicet dependet poſterius, non autem de illo quod aliquo modo eſt prius, à quo ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men poſterius non dependet eſſentialiter.</hi> He ſpeaks of things Natural and Phyſical, but it is alſo appliable unto things mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral. The omiſſion of a duty that is by Gods command An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tecedent unto another, doth not ſuſpend, much leſſe nullifie the Obligation unto the conſequent duty; unleſſe there be an eſſentiall dependency of the conſequent duty upon the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tecedent duty.</p>
            <p>But now to make application of this unto the Lords Supper; Although the Presbyterating of a Church, and the exerciſe of Juriſdiction by an Elderſhip be enjoyned by God as An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tecedents unto the adminiſtration and receiving of the Lords Supper; yet it doth not hereupon follow, that upon want of an Elderſhip, an omiſſion of the exerciſe of Juriſdiction, the command to adminiſter and receive is ſuſpended, much leſs extinguiſhed; unleſs you can prove, that there is an eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſential dependency of the adminiſtration and receiving of the Lords Supper upon the Presbyterating of the Church, in which it is adminiſtred, and the exerciſe of jurisdiction therein.
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:115045:40"/>It implieth a contradiction, and is utterly impoſſible for a thing to be without that upon which it eſſentially dependeth: But it doth not imply a contradiction, it is not impoſſible for the Lords Supper to be adminiſtred and received in an Un-Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterated Church; Therefore the adminiſtration and receiving of the Lords Supper doth not eſſentially depend upon the Presbyterating of a Church, upon its having Ruling-Elders; and conſequently the Command of adminiſtring and receiving the Lords Supper is not in reference unto the Command of ſetling an Elderſhip, only a mediate Command. Unto the proofe of this Mr <hi>Fullwood</hi> may apply thoſe Arguments al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leadged by me to prove, That the excluſion of ſcandalous and groſſe ignorant perſons is not a neceſſary Antecedent un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the adminiſtration of the Lords Supper by Phyſical Obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation, unto which Mr <hi>Fullwood</hi> hath given no anſwer at all.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Suppoſe we ſhould grant, that the Command of adminiſtring and receiving the Lords Supper be mediate, with reference to the Presbyterating of a Church, yet Mr <hi>Full<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wood</hi> will gaine little thereby, if he underſtand, as he muſt, the Command concerning the Presbyterating of a Church to be not <hi>de Eventu,</hi> but only <hi>de Conatu;</hi> and if withall he put a difference betwen guilty and innocent perſons, thoſe who hinder or do not what lyeth in them to farther the ſetling of an Elderſhip; and thoſe who pray, ſigh, and uſe all other law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full meanes for the compaſſing of it. That the Command to have a Church Presbyterated, to have Ruling Elders, is to be taken only <hi>de Conatu,</hi> concerning an endeavour of it, will not, I think, be denied by Mr <hi>Fullwood.</hi> And indeed, it were not unreaſonable to underſtand it <hi>de Eventu,</hi> concerning the event, concerning an actual Presbyterating of the Church: for that may not be in our power to effect. The whole Church may be over-powred by the Magiſtrate, and the beſt affected Party in a Church may be over-borne by a Major part that may be diſ-affected unto Presbytery: Now if it ſhould be granted unto Mr <hi>Fullwood,</hi> That the Command to receive the Lords Supper did not bind immediately, but only mediately, upon pre-ſuppoſal that we had done our endeavour, and uſed all lawful meanes for the erecting of an Elderſhip; I do won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:115045:40"/>what advantage ſuch a Conceſſion can yeild unto his cauſe But now if he ſhall contend, that after we have uſed our ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt endeavour to erect an Elderſhip, and cannot poſſibly prevaile, that we are then by that which is meerly the fault of others, diſ-obliged from the receiving the Lords Supper. Firſt, I ſay that for this aſſertion Mr <hi>Fullwood</hi> cannot bring ſo much as any colourable Argument. Then ſecondly, It makes the Lords Supper to have an eſſential dependence upon an Elder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, which I have before refuted.</p>
            <p>The ſecond only thing that is conſiderable in Mr <hi>Fullwoods</hi> Book, is an Objection which I ſhall give you in his own words and then returne a brief anſwer unto it.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter">
               <body>
                  <head>
                     <hi>Mr</hi> Fullwood.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>While we will uſe this Sacrament in a Church <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>n-Presbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated do we not thus directly oppoſe and violate that Command of the Spirit of God by the Apoſtle,</hi> 1 Cor. 4. ult. Let all things be done in order. <hi>We on both ſides acknowledge that there ſhould be the exerciſe and act of Juriſdiction, that there ſhould be Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling Elders elected and ſetled in our Churches for the ſame end, for our more orderly proceeding in this holy exerciſe: But becauſe we cannot have an Elderſhip as, and ſo ſoon as we would, we will have the Sacrament as, and ſo ſoon as we can, If we cannot have it with, we will have it without our Saviours, or any order; how keep we then the named Precept,</hi> do all things, <hi>and this ſure amongſt the reſt,</hi> do all things in order. <hi>Firſt, ſettle Elderſhip, then upon their preparitive work, by the acts and exerciſe of their Juriſdiction adminiſter the Sacrament according unto our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours order.</hi>
                  </p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>
               <label>Anſwer.</label>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe Miniſters and people that have done their endeavour and uſed all lawfull means for the ſetling of an Elderſhip, do not at all violate the command of the Spirit, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.40. Neither doth that which you ſay prove it at all, as will eaſily appear; if you pleaſe to put your Argument into forme; for then it ſtands thus. If there ſhould be the exerciſe and act of Jurisdiction, if there ſhould be Ruling-Elders elected and ſetled in our Churches for our more orderly proceeding in the adminiſtration of the Lords Supper; then thoſe that have uſed all lawfull means for the exerciſe of Juriſdiction, for the election and ſetling of Ruling-Elders and cannot prevaile, they
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:115045:41"/>directly oppoſe and violate that command of the Spirit. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.40. if they adminiſter and receive the Lords Supper. The conſequent is moſt extreamly falſe, and is not back'd ſo much as by any colour or ſhadow of reaſon. And indeed you can never make it good, unleſſe you can prove either that there is an eſſentiall dependency of the Lords Supper upon the Elder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, or elſe that there is a command to delay and deferre the adminiſtration of the Lords Supper until an Elderſhip be erected.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter">
               <body>
                  <head>
                     <hi>Mr.</hi> Fullwood.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Moreover this Command hath with it the force of a Negative, namely let nothing be done in diſorder.</hi>
                  </p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>
               <label>Anſwer.</label>
            </p>
            <p>This Propoſition, Let nothing be done in diſorder is ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guous and may be underſtood two wayes.</p>
            <p>Firſt, as a prohibition of diſorder and confuſion in the Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, and Ordinances of God; and ſo it is granted and the conceſſion of it will not prejudice any thing that I affirme.</p>
            <p>Next it may be taken as a prohibition given generally unto every one of that Worſhip and Ordinances of God, wherein there is any diſorder committed by our ſelves or others, (though without our default) And ſo it is very untrue; and if granted concerning the diſorder of others, would open a gapp unto a totall neglect of publike prayers, hearing of the Word. For unto thoſe Ordinances wicked men come diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orderly, becauſe unpreparedly. Other mens violation and breach of order doth not diſoblige us from the Worſhip and Ordinances of God; eſpecially when we are innocent of ſuch their diſorder. Nay, if we underſtand the Words as a Prohi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition of that Worſhip and Ordinance, wherin there is any diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>order committed: even ſo they are not generally true; for though we come with diſorder &amp; unpreparednes unto the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of the Word, and publike prayers; yet we are not for this diſorder to omit publike prayers, and hearing of the Word: for this were the way not to prevent, but to multiply our ſin; and yet I do not deny, but that this diſorder &amp; unpreparednes is a great ſin, for which we ought to be humbled.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
